<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="KR4a0001-en">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>楚辭 (en)</title>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt><edition><idno type="kanripo">KR4a0001</idno></edition></editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p>Published electronically</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
 <p>Generated from the TLS textfiles in Kanripo format on 2018-10-02</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div><head>1 離騷經</head>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-1a.3" xml:lang="en">(I am) a scion of the High Lord Gāo Yáng,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-1a.4" xml:lang="en">Bó Yōng was my father's name.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-1a.5" xml:lang="en">When the Shè Tí (star) pointed to the first month of the year,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-1a.6" xml:lang="en">On a gēngyín day I went on to get born???.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-1a.7" xml:lang="en">My honoured father, inspecting they way I first came into this world,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-1a.8" xml:lang="en">and in the beginning he conferred on me a distinguished name.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-1a.9" xml:lang="en">He gave me the personal name Zhèng Zé.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-1a.10" xml:lang="en">and he gave me the given name Líng Jūn.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-1a.11" xml:lang="en">In dazzling abundance I have - (on the one hand) - this inner beauty</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-1a.12" xml:lang="en">and in addition I have added to it a refined appearance</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-1a.13" xml:lang="en">I dressed in jiānglí and bìzhǐ aromatic plants</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-1a.14" xml:lang="en">and twined autumn orchids to make a pendant.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-1a.15" xml:lang="en">I raced along, as if I would never catch up (with it)</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-1a.16" xml:lang="en">afraid that time would not stay with me.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-1a.17" xml:lang="en">In the morning [zhāo qiān bī] I gathered the angelica on the mountains;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-1a.18" xml:lang="en">In the evening I plucked the sùmǎng aromatic on the sandy islet.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-1a.19" xml:lang="en">17 The days and months hurried on, never delaying;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-1a.20" xml:lang="en">Springs and autumns sped by in endles alternation:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-1a.21" xml:lang="en">I thought about the plants withering and dropping their leaves,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-1a.22" xml:lang="en">and I was afraid that for the Fair One it will be too late.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-1a.23" xml:lang="en">'You are not warmly supporting the vigorous but rejecting the (morally) filthy:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-1a.24" xml:lang="en">why will you not make improvements to this standard of conduct?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-1a.25" xml:lang="en">I mount brave coursers and gallop along</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-1a.26" xml:lang="en">Come, I shall guide you, won't you; I shall lead the way.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-2a.2" xml:lang="en">The Three Sovereigns of old in their purity</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-2a.3" xml:lang="en">were the ones with whom all the world's fragrances took their abode.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-2a.4" xml:lang="en">They brought together pepper and cinnamon;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-2a.5" xml:lang="en">and how should it have been only the huìchén that they twined into garlands.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-2a.6" xml:lang="en">Glorious and great [gěng jiè] were those two, Yáo and Shùn,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-2a.7" xml:lang="en">since they kept to the right Way and found the right Road.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-2a.8" xml:lang="en">And how madly unrestrained were Jié and Zhòu,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-2a.9" xml:lang="en">precisely because they made convenient use of shortcuts and (in the end) got nowhere.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-2a.10" xml:lang="en">33 'The conspirators are the ones who take the secret pleasures</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-2a.11" xml:lang="en">But their way is dark and leads to danger.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-2a.12" xml:lang="en">How should I personally (ich fuer meine Person) fear disaster</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-2a.13" xml:lang="en">I am terrified that the royal chariot may be ruined.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-2a.14" xml:lang="en">Quickly I raced about, went forward and towards the back.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-2a.15" xml:lang="en">reaching the footprints of the bygone kings.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-2a.16" xml:lang="en">But the Fragrant One refused to examine my true feelings:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-2a.17" xml:lang="en">He lent ear instead to slander, and raged against me.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-2a.18" xml:lang="en">41 How well I understand how outspokenness brings disaster;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-2a.19" xml:lang="en">(yet) I bear with this, and am unable to discontinue (my outspokenness).</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-2a.20" xml:lang="en">I point to Ninefold Heaven and take it to be my witness</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-2a.21" xml:lang="en">And all for the sake of the Spiritual Fair One.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-2a.22" xml:lang="en">INTERPOLATION</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-2a.24" xml:lang="en">Although in the beginning he exchanged views with me in frankness;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-2a.25" xml:lang="en">afterwards he regretted this, hid away (from me) and changed his mind.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-2a.26" xml:lang="en">Although I do not have difficulties being serparated</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-2a.27" xml:lang="en">But it grieves me to find the Fair One so inconstant.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.2" xml:lang="en">49 I had tended nine twenty-acres fields of orchids,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.3" xml:lang="en">And planted a hundred acres of melilotus;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.4" xml:lang="en">I made fields of liúyí flowers and of</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.5" xml:lang="en">In mixed beds (I planted) dùhéng and fragrant zhǐ flowers.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.6" xml:lang="en">And hoped that when leaf and stem were in their full prime,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.7" xml:lang="en">I hoped, when the time had come, to harvest these.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.8" xml:lang="en">Even if they should wither and perish, what harm will this do to me?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.9" xml:lang="en">But I grieve that all my blossoms should waste in rank weeds.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.10" xml:lang="en">57 All others press forward in greed and gluttony,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.11" xml:lang="en">No surfeit satiating their demands:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.12" xml:lang="en">Forgiving themselves, but harshly judging others;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.13" xml:lang="en">Each fretting his heart away in envy and malice.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.14" xml:lang="en">Madly they rush in the covetous chase,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.15" xml:lang="en">But not after that which my heart sets store by. [is eager for]</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.16" xml:lang="en">For old age comes creeping and soon will be upon me,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.17" xml:lang="en">And I fear I shall not leave behind an enduring name.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.18" xml:lang="en">65 In the mornings I drank the dew that fell from the magnolia;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.19" xml:lang="en">At evening ate the petals that dropped from chrysanthemums.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.20" xml:lang="en">If only my real inner feelings are truly beautiful,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.21" xml:lang="en">I do not care that I keep being emaciated.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.22" xml:lang="en">I pulled up roots to bind the valerian</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.23" xml:lang="en">And threat the castor plant's fallen clusters with;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.24" xml:lang="en">I trimmed sprays of cassia for plaiting melilotus,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.25" xml:lang="en">I plait the húshēng plant so it becomes nice and long.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.26" xml:lang="en">73 I take my fashion from the men of old:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.27" xml:lang="en">A garb unlike that which the rude world cares for:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.28" xml:lang="en">Though it may not accord with present-day manners,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.29" xml:lang="en">I will follow the pattern that Péng Xián has left.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.30" xml:lang="en">I heave a long sigh, and then I cover my tears,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.31" xml:lang="en">I bemoan that poor man as long as he lives, is suffers so much hardship.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.32" xml:lang="en">I may have loved the cultivation of beauty, and made that my bridle and reins,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.33" xml:lang="en">but I was so frank, I was slandered in the morning and cast off that same evening.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.34" xml:lang="en">Yet, though cast off, I would wear my orchid girdle;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.35" xml:lang="en">I would pluck some angelicas to add to its beauty;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.36" xml:lang="en">For this it is what my heart takes most delight in, [regards as good]</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.37" xml:lang="en">And though I died nine times, I should not regret it.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.38" xml:lang="en">What I regret is the Fair One's waywardness:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.39" xml:lang="en">That never once stops to ask what is in men's minds.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.40" xml:lang="en">All your ladies were jealous of my delicate beauty;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.41" xml:lang="en">In their spiteful chattering they said I was given to wantonness.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.42" xml:lang="en">89 Truly this generation are cunning artificers,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.43" xml:lang="en">From square and compass turn their eyes and change the true measurement</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.44" xml:lang="en">Disregard the ruled line to follow their crooked fancies;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.45" xml:lang="en">To emulate in flattery is their only rule.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.46" xml:lang="en">But I am sick and sad at heart and stand irresolute:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.47" xml:lang="en">I alone am at a loss in this generation.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.48" xml:lang="en">But I would rather quicly die and meet dissolution</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.49" xml:lang="en">Before I ever would consent to ape their behaviour.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.50" xml:lang="en">97 Eagles do not flock like birds of lesser speicies;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.51" xml:lang="en">From bygone generations onwards this has invariably/inherently been so.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.52" xml:lang="en">How can the round and the square ever fit together?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.53" xml:lang="en">How can different ways of life be reconciled?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.54" xml:lang="en">Yet humbling one's spirit and curbing one's pride,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.55" xml:lang="en">Bearing blame humbly and enduring insults,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.56" xml:lang="en">But keeping pure and spotless and dying in righteousness:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-3a.57" xml:lang="en">Such conduct was greatly prized by the wise men of old.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-4a.2" xml:lang="en">105 Repenting, therefore, that I had not conned the way more closely,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-4a.3" xml:lang="en">I halted, intending to turn back again -</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-4a.4" xml:lang="en">turned about my chariot and retrace my road</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-4a.5" xml:lang="en">before I had gone astray too far.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-4a.6" xml:lang="en">I walked my horses through the marsh's orchid-covered margin;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-4a.7" xml:lang="en">I galloped to the hill of pepper-trees and rested there.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-4a.8" xml:lang="en">When stepping forward I did not go in, because I felt I would meet criticism.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-4a.9" xml:lang="en">And so, retired, I would once more fashion my former raiment.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-4a.10" xml:lang="en">113 I made a coat of lotus and water-chestnut leaves,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-4a.11" xml:lang="en">And gathered lotus petals to make myself a skirt.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-4a.12" xml:lang="en">I will not longer care that no one understands me,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-4a.13" xml:lang="en">As long as I can keep the sweet fragrance of my mind.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-4a.14" xml:lang="en">Higher still was my hat, towering as it was.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-4a.15" xml:lang="en">Long was the girlde, dangling from my waist.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-4a.16" xml:lang="en">Fragrant and foul mingle in confusion.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-4a.17" xml:lang="en">But my inner brightness has remained undimmed.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-4a.18" xml:lang="en">121 Suddenly I turned back and let my eyes wander.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-4a.19" xml:lang="en">I resolved to go and visit all the world's quarters.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-4a.20" xml:lang="en">The pendants on my belt are all in confusion, multifariously adorned</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-4a.21" xml:lang="en">and the fragrance wafts richly to become more and more manifest.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-4a.22" xml:lang="en">All men have something in their lives that gives them pleasure:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-4a.23" xml:lang="en">With me the love of beauty is my constant joy.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-4a.24" xml:lang="en">I could not change this, even if my body were dismembered;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-4a.25" xml:lang="en">For how could dismemberment ever hurt my mind?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.2" xml:lang="en">129 My Nǚ Xū was fearful and clung to me imploringly,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.3" xml:lang="en">Lifting her voice up in expostulation:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.4" xml:lang="en">'Gǔn in his stubbornness took no thought for his life</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.5" xml:lang="en">And perished, as result, on the moor of Feather Mountain.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.6" xml:lang="en">Why are you so broadly orientated and outspoken, and fond of beauty,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.7" xml:lang="en">why in your confusion do you have these attractive ornaments?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.8" xml:lang="en">Thorns, king-grass, curly-ear hold the place of power:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.9" xml:lang="en">But you must needs stand apart and not speak them fair.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.10" xml:lang="en">137 You cannot go from door to door convincing everybody;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.11" xml:lang="en">No one can say, "See, look into my mind!"</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.12" xml:lang="en">Others band together and like to have companions:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.13" xml:lang="en">Why must you be so aloof? Why not heed my councel?"</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.14" xml:lang="en">But I look to the wise men of old for my guidance:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.15" xml:lang="en">So sighing, with a full heart, I have gone through all this.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.16" xml:lang="en">And crossing the Yuán and Xiāng, I jorneyed southwards</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.17" xml:lang="en">until I came to Chóng Huā and stated my case (to him).</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.18" xml:lang="en">145 'Singing the Nine Songs and dancing the Nine Changes,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.19" xml:lang="en">Qi(?) of Xià made revelry and knew no restraint,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.20" xml:lang="en">Taking no thought for the troubles that would follow:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.21" xml:lang="en">And so his five sons fell out, brother against brother.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.22" xml:lang="en">Yì loved idle roaming and hunting to distraction,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.23" xml:lang="en">And took delight in shooting at the mighty foxes.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.24" xml:lang="en">But foolish dissipation has seldom a good end:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.25" xml:lang="en">And Han(?) Zhuó covetously took his master's wife.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.26" xml:lang="en">153 'Zhuó's son, Jiāo, put on his strong armour</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.27" xml:lang="en">And wreaked his wild will without any restraint.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.28" xml:lang="en">The days passed in pleasure; far he forgot himself,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.29" xml:lang="en">Till his head came tumbling down from his shoulders.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.30" xml:lang="en">Jiē of Xià was constantly offending the rules of proper behaviour.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.31" xml:lang="en">And so he came finally to meet with calamity.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.32" xml:lang="en">Zhòu cut up and salted the bodies of his ministers;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.33" xml:lang="en">And so the days were numbered of the hereditory House of Yīn.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.34" xml:lang="en">161 'Táng of Shāng and Yǔ of Xià were reverent and respectful;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.35" xml:lang="en">The House of Zhōu chose the true way without error,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.36" xml:lang="en">Raising up the virtuous and able men to government,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.37" xml:lang="en">Following the straight line without fear or favour.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.38" xml:lang="en">High God in Heaven knows no partiality;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.39" xml:lang="en">He looks for the virtuous and makes them his ministers.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.40" xml:lang="en">For only the wise and good can ever flourish</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.41" xml:lang="en">If it is given them to possess the earth.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.42" xml:lang="en">169' I have looked back into the past and forward to later ages,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.43" xml:lang="en">Examining the outcome of men's different designs.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.44" xml:lang="en">Where is the unrighteous man who could be trusted?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.45" xml:lang="en">Where is the wicked man whose service could be used?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.46" xml:lang="en">Though I stand at the pit's mouth and death yawns before me,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.47" xml:lang="en">I still feel no regret at the course I have chosen.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.48" xml:lang="en">Straightening the handle, regardless of the socket's shape:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.49" xml:lang="en">For that crime the good men of old were hacked in pieces.'</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.50" xml:lang="en">177 Many a heavy sigh I heaved in my despair,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.51" xml:lang="en">Grieving that I was born in such an unlucky time.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.52" xml:lang="en">I plucked soft lotus petals to wipe my welling tears</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-5a.53" xml:lang="en">That fell down in rivers and wet my coat front.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.2" xml:lang="en">I knelt on my outspread skirts and poured my plaint out,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.3" xml:lang="en">And the righteousness within me was clearly manifest.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.4" xml:lang="en">I yoked a team of jade dragons to a phoenix-figured car</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.5" xml:lang="en">And waited for the wind to come, to soar up on my journey.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.6" xml:lang="en">185 I started in the morning on my way from Cāng-wú.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.7" xml:lang="en">By evening I had arrived at the Hanging Garden.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.8" xml:lang="en">I wanted to stay a while in those fairy precincts,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.9" xml:lang="en">But the swift-moving sun was dipping to the west.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.10" xml:lang="en">I ordered Xī Hé to stay the sun-steeds' gallop,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.11" xml:lang="en">To stand over Yān-zī mountain and not go in;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.12" xml:lang="en">For the road was so far and so distant was my journey:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.13" xml:lang="en">And I wanted to go up and down, seeking my heart's desire.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.14" xml:lang="en">193 I watered my dragon steeds at the Pool of Heaven,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.15" xml:lang="en">And tied their reins up to the Fú-sāng tree.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.16" xml:lang="en">I broke a sprig of the Ruò tree to strike the sun with:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.17" xml:lang="en">First I would roam a little for my enjoyment.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.18" xml:lang="en">I sent Wàng Shū ahead to ride before me;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.19" xml:lang="en">The Wind God went behind as my outrider;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.20" xml:lang="en">The Bird of Heaven gave notice of my comings;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.21" xml:lang="en">The Thunder God warned me when all was not ready.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.22" xml:lang="en">201 I caused my phoenixes to mount on their pinions</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.23" xml:lang="en">And fly ever onward by night and by day.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.24" xml:lang="en">The whirlwinds gathered and came out to meet me,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.25" xml:lang="en">Leading clouds and rainbows, to give me welcome.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.26" xml:lang="en">In wild confusion, now joined and now parted,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.27" xml:lang="en">Upwards and downwards rushed the glittering train.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.28" xml:lang="en">I asked Heaven's porter to open up for me;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.29" xml:lang="en">But he leant across Heaven's gate and eyed me churlishly.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.30" xml:lang="en">209 The day was getting dark and drawing to its close.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.31" xml:lang="en">Knotting orchids, I waited in indecision.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.32" xml:lang="en">The muddy, impure world, so undiscriminating,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.33" xml:lang="en">Seeks always to hide beauty, out of jealousy.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.34" xml:lang="en">I decided when morning came to cross the White Water,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.35" xml:lang="en">And climbed the peak of Làng Fēng, and there tied up my steeds.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.36" xml:lang="en">Then I looked about me and suddenly burst out weeping,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.37" xml:lang="en">Because on that high hill there was no fair lady.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.38" xml:lang="en">217 'Here I am, suddenly, in this House of Spring,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.39" xml:lang="en">I have broken off a jasper branch to add to my girdle.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.40" xml:lang="en">Before the jasper flowers have shed their bright petals,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.41" xml:lang="en">I shall look for a maiden below to give it to.'</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.42" xml:lang="en">So I made Fēng Lóng ride off on a cloud</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.43" xml:lang="en">To seek out the dwelling-place of the lady Fú Fēi.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.44" xml:lang="en">I took off my girdle as a pledge of my suit to her, [my pendants on the belt]</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.45" xml:lang="en">And ordered Lame Beauty to be the go-between.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.50" xml:lang="en">With proud disdain she guarded her beauty,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.51" xml:lang="en">Passing each day in idle, wanton pleasures.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.52" xml:lang="en">Though fair she may be, she lacks all seemliness:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.53" xml:lang="en">Come! I'll have none of her; let us search elsewhere!</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.54" xml:lang="en">233 I looked all around over the earth's four quarters,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.55" xml:lang="en">Circling the heavens till at last I alighted.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.56" xml:lang="en">I gazed on a jade tower's glittering splendour</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.57" xml:lang="en">And spied the lovely daughter of the Lord of Sōng.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.58" xml:lang="en">I sent off the magpie to pay my court to her,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.59" xml:lang="en">But the magpie told me that my suit had gone amiss.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.60" xml:lang="en">The magpie flew off with noisy chatterings:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.61" xml:lang="en">I hate him for an idle, knavish fellow.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.62" xml:lang="en">241. My mind was irresolute and wavering;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.63" xml:lang="en">I wanted to go, and yet I could not. (zìshì)</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.64" xml:lang="en">Already the phoenix had taken his present,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.65" xml:lang="en">And I feared that Gāo Xīn would get there before me.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.66" xml:lang="en">I wanted to go far away, but had nowhere to go to:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.67" xml:lang="en">Where could I wander to look for amusment?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.68" xml:lang="en">Before they were married to Prince Shǎo Kāng,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.69" xml:lang="en">Lord Yú's two daughters were there for the wooing.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.70" xml:lang="en">249 But my pleader was weak and my matchmaker stupid,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.71" xml:lang="en">And I feared that this suit, too, would not be successful:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.72" xml:lang="en">For the world is impure and envious of the able,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.73" xml:lang="en">Eager to hide men's good and make much of the their ill.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.74" xml:lang="en">Deep in the palace, unapproachable,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.75" xml:lang="en">The wise king slumbers and will not be awakened;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.76" xml:lang="en">That the thoughts in my breast should all go unuttered -</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-6a.77" xml:lang="en">How can I endure this until I end my days?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.2" xml:lang="en">257 I searched for the holy plant and twigs of bamboo,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.3" xml:lang="en">And ordered Líng Fēn to make divinations for me.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.4" xml:lang="en">He said, 'Beauty is always bound to find its mate.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.5" xml:lang="en">Who that was truly fair was ever without lovers?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.6" xml:lang="en">Think of the vastness of the wide world:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.7" xml:lang="en">Here is not the only place where you can find your lady.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.8" xml:lang="en">Go farther afield', he said, 'and do not be faint-hearted.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.9" xml:lang="en">What woman seeking handsome mate could ever refuse you?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.10" xml:lang="en">265 "What place on earth does not boast some fragrant flower?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.11" xml:lang="en">Why need you always cleave to your old home?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.12" xml:lang="en">The world today is blinded with its own folly:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.13" xml:lang="en">You cannot make people see the virtue inside you. (mine! CH)</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.14" xml:lang="en">Most people's loathings and likings are different,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.15" xml:lang="en">Only these men here are not as others are;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.16" xml:lang="en">For they wear mugwort and cram their waistbands with it;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.17" xml:lang="en">But the lovely valley orchid they deem unfit to wear.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.18" xml:lang="en">273 'Since beauty of flower, then, and of shrub escapes them,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.19" xml:lang="en">What chance has a rarest jewel of gaining recognition?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.20" xml:lang="en">They gather up muck to stuff their perfume bags with;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.21" xml:lang="en">The spicy pepper-plant they say has got no scent at all.'</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.22" xml:lang="en">I wanted to follow Líng Fēn's auspicious oracle,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.23" xml:lang="en">But I faltered and could not make my mind up.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.24" xml:lang="en">I heard that Wū Xián was descending in the evening,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.25" xml:lang="en">So I lay in wait with offerings of peppered rice-balls.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.26" xml:lang="en">2ī The spirits came like a dense cloud descending,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.27" xml:lang="en">And the host of Doubting mountain came crowding to meet him.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.28" xml:lang="en">His godhead was manifested by a blaze of radiance,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.29" xml:lang="en">And he addressed me in these auspicious words:</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.30" xml:lang="en">'To and fro in the earth you must everywhere wander,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.31" xml:lang="en">Seeking one whose thoughts are of your own measure.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.32" xml:lang="en">Tāng and Yǔ sought sincerely for the right helpers;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.33" xml:lang="en">So Yi(?) Yin(?) and Gāo Yáo worked well with their princes.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.34" xml:lang="en">289 'As long as your soul within is beautiful,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.35" xml:lang="en">What need have you of a matchmaker?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.36" xml:lang="en">Yuè laboured as a builder, pounding earth at Fù112-Yán,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.37" xml:lang="en">Yet Wǔ Dīng employed him without a second thought.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.38" xml:lang="en">Lǚ Wàng wielded the butcher's knife at Zhao(?)-ge(?),</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.39" xml:lang="en">But King Wén met him and raised him up on high.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.40" xml:lang="en">Ní4ng Qī sang as he fed his ox at evening;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.41" xml:lang="en">Duke Huán of Qí heard him and took him as his minister.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.42" xml:lang="en">297 'Gather the flower of youth before it is too late,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.43" xml:lang="en">While the good season is still not yet over.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.44" xml:lang="en">Beware lest the shrike sound his note before the equinox,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.45" xml:lang="en">Causing all the flowers to lose their fine fragrance.'</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.46" xml:lang="en">How splendid the glitter of my jasper girdle!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.47" xml:lang="en">But the crowd make a dark screen, masking its beauty.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.48" xml:lang="en">And I fear that my enemies, who never can be trusted,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.49" xml:lang="en">Will break it out of spiteful jealousy.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.50" xml:lang="en">305 The age is disordered in a tumult of changing:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.51" xml:lang="en">How can I tarry much longer among them?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.52" xml:lang="en">Orchid and iris have lost all their fragrance;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.53" xml:lang="en">Flag and melilotus have changed into straw.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.54" xml:lang="en">Why have all the fragrant flowers of days gone by</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.55" xml:lang="en">Now all transformed themselves into worthless mugwort?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.56" xml:lang="en">What other reason can there be for this</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.57" xml:lang="en">But that they all have no more care for beauty?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.58" xml:lang="en">313 I thought that orchid was one to be trusted,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.59" xml:lang="en">But he proved a sham, bent only on pleasing his masters.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.60" xml:lang="en">He overcame his goodness and conformed to evil counsels:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.61" xml:lang="en">He no more deserves to rank with fragrant flowers.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.62" xml:lang="en">Pepper is all wagging tongue and lives only for slander;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.63" xml:lang="en">And even stinking dogwood seeks to fill a perfume bag.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.64" xml:lang="en">Since they only seek advancement and labour for position,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.65" xml:lang="en">What fragrance have they deserving our respect?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.66" xml:lang="en">321 Since, then, the world's way is to drift the way the tide runs,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.67" xml:lang="en">Who can stay the same and not change with all the rest?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.68" xml:lang="en">Seeing the bahaviour of orchid and pepper-flower,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.69" xml:lang="en">What can be expected of cart-halt and selinea?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.70" xml:lang="en">They have cast off their beauty and come to this:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.71" xml:lang="en">Only my garland is left to treasure.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.72" xml:lang="en">Its penetrating perfume does not easily desert it,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.73" xml:lang="en">And even to this day its fragrance has not faded.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.74" xml:lang="en">329. I will follow my natural bent and please myself;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.75" xml:lang="en">I will go off wandering to look for a lady.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.76" xml:lang="en">While my adornment is in its pristine beauty</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-7a.77" xml:lang="en">I will travel all around looking both high and low.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.2" xml:lang="en">Since Líng Fēn had given me a favourable oracle,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.3" xml:lang="en">I picked an auspicious day to start my journey on.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.4" xml:lang="en">I broke a branch of jasper to take for my meat,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.5" xml:lang="en">And ground fine jasper meal for my journey's provisions.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.6" xml:lang="en">337 'Harness winged dragons to be my coursers;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.7" xml:lang="en">Let my chariot be of fine work of jade and ivory!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.8" xml:lang="en">How can I live with men whose hearts are strangers to me?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.9" xml:lang="en">I am going a far journey to be away from them.'</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.10" xml:lang="en">I took the way that led towards the Kūn-lún mountain:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.11" xml:lang="en">A long, long road with many a turning in it.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.12" xml:lang="en">The cloud-embroidered banner flapped its great shade above us;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.13" xml:lang="en">And the jinging jade joke-bells tinkled merrily.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.14" xml:lang="en">345 I set off at morning from the Ford of Heaven;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.15" xml:lang="en">At evening I cam to the world's western end.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.16" xml:lang="en">Phoenixes followed me, bearing up my pennants,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.17" xml:lang="en">Soaring high aloft with majestic wing-beats.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.18" xml:lang="en">'See I have come to the Desert of Moving Sands!"</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.19" xml:lang="en">Warily I drove along the banks of the Red Water,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.20" xml:lang="en">Then, beckoning the water-dragons to make a bridge for me,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.21" xml:lang="en">I summoned the God of the West to take me over.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.22" xml:lang="en">353 So long the road had been and full of difficulties;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.23" xml:lang="en">I sent word to my escorts to take another route.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.24" xml:lang="en">To wheel around leftwards, skirting Bù-Zhōu Mountain:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.25" xml:lang="en">On the shore of the Western Sea we would reassemble.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.26" xml:lang="en">When we had mustered there, all thousand chariots,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.27" xml:lang="en">Jade hub to jade hub we galloped on abreast.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.28" xml:lang="en">My eight dragon steeds flew on with writhing undulations;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.29" xml:lang="en">My cloud-embroidered banners flapped on the wind.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.30" xml:lang="en">361 In wain I tried to curb them, to slacken the swift pace:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.31" xml:lang="en">But the spirits soared high up, far into the distance.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.32" xml:lang="en">We played the Nine Songs and danced the Shao dances:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.33" xml:lang="en">Borrowing the time to make a holiday.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.34" xml:lang="en">But when I had ascended the splendour of the heavens,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.35" xml:lang="en">I suddenly caught a glimpse below of my old home.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.36" xml:lang="en">The groom's heart was heavy and the horses for longing</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-8a.37" xml:lang="en">Arched their heads back and refused to to go on.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-9a.2" xml:lang="en">LUAN</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-9a.3" xml:lang="en">369 Enough!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-9a.4" xml:lang="en">There are no true men in the state: no one understands me.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-9a.5" xml:lang="en">Why should I cleave to the city of my birth?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-9a.6" xml:lang="en">Since none is worthy to work with in making good government,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_001-9a.7" xml:lang="en">I will go and join Péng Xián in the place where he abides.</seg>
</p>
<p>
</p>
</div>
<div><head>2 九歌</head>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-2a.1" xml:lang="en">The Great Unity, God of the Eastern Sky</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-2a.2" xml:lang="en">1On a lucky day with an auspicious name</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-2a.3" xml:lang="en">Reverently we come to delight the Lord on High.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-2a.4" xml:lang="en">We grasp the long sword's haft of jade,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-2a.5" xml:lang="en">And our girdle pendants clash and chime.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-2a.6" xml:lang="en">5 From the god's jewelled mat with treasures laden</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-2a.7" xml:lang="en">Take up the fragrant flower-offerings,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-2a.8" xml:lang="en">The meats cooked in melilotus, served on orchid mats,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-2a.9" xml:lang="en">And libations of cinnamon wine and pepper sauces!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-2a.10" xml:lang="en">Flourish the drumsticks, beat the drums!</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-2a.11" xml:lang="en">10 The singing begins softly to a slow, solemn measure;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-2a.12" xml:lang="en">Then, as pipes and zithers join in, the sound grows shirller.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-2a.13" xml:lang="en">Now the priestesses come, splendid in their gogeous apparel,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-2a.14" xml:lang="en">And the hall is filled with a penetrating fragrance</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-2a.15" xml:lang="en">The five notes mingle in a rich harmony;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-2a.16" xml:lang="en">15 And the god is merry and takes his pleasure.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-4a.1" xml:lang="en">The Lord within the Clouds</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-4a.2" xml:lang="en">We have bathed in orchid water and washed our hair with perfumes,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-4a.3" xml:lang="en">And dressed ourselves like flowers in embroidered clothing.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-4a.4" xml:lang="en">The god has halted, swaying, above us,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-4a.5" xml:lang="en">Shining with a persistent radiance.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-4a.6" xml:lang="en">5 He is going to rest in the House of Life.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-4a.7" xml:lang="en">His brightness is like that of the sun and moon.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-4a.8" xml:lang="en">In his dragon chariot, dressed in imperial splendour,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-4a.9" xml:lang="en">Now he flies off to wander round the sky.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-4a.10" xml:lang="en">The god had just descended in bright majesty,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-4a.11" xml:lang="en">10 When off in a whirl he soared again, far into the clouds.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-4a.12" xml:lang="en">He looks down on Jì-zhōu and the lands beyond it;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-4a.13" xml:lang="en">There is no place in the world that he does not pass over.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-4a.14" xml:lang="en">Thinking of that lord makes me sigh</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-4a.15" xml:lang="en">And afflicts my heart with a grievous longing.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.1" xml:lang="en">The Goddess of the Xiāng</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.2" xml:lang="en">1 The goddess comes not, she holds back shyly.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.3" xml:lang="en">Who keeps her delaying within the island,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.4" xml:lang="en">Lady of the lovely eyes and the winning smile?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.5" xml:lang="en">Skimming the water in my cassia boat,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.6" xml:lang="en">5 I bid the Yuán and Xiāng still their waves</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.7" xml:lang="en">And the Great River make its stream flow softly.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.8" xml:lang="en">I look for the goddess, but she does not come yet.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.9" xml:lang="en">Of whom does she think as she plays her reed-pipes?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.10" xml:lang="en">North I go, drawn by my flying dragon,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.11" xml:lang="en">10 Steering my course to the Dòng-tíng lake:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.12" xml:lang="en">My sail is of fig-leaves, melilotus my rigging,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.13" xml:lang="en">And iris my flag-pole, my banner of orchids.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.14" xml:lang="en">Gazing at the distant Cén-yáng mooring,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.15" xml:lang="en">I waft my magic across the Great River.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.16" xml:lang="en">15 I waft my magic, but it does not reach her.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.17" xml:lang="en">The lady is sad, and sighs for me;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.18" xml:lang="en">And my tears run down over cheek and chin:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.19" xml:lang="en">I am choked with longing for my lady.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.20" xml:lang="en">My cassia oars and orchid sweep</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.21" xml:lang="en">20 Chip all in vain at ice and snow.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.22" xml:lang="en">I am gathering wild figs in the water!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.23" xml:lang="en">I am looking for lotuses in the tree-tops!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.24" xml:lang="en">The wooing is useless if hearts are divided;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.25" xml:lang="en">The love that is not deep is quickly broken.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.26" xml:lang="en">25 The stream runs fast through the stony shallows,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.27" xml:lang="en">And my flying dragon wings swiftly above it.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.28" xml:lang="en">The pain is more lasting if loving is faithless:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.29" xml:lang="en">She broke her tryst; she told me she had not time.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.30" xml:lang="en">In the morning I race by the bank of the river;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.31" xml:lang="en">30 At evening I halt at this north island.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.32" xml:lang="en">The birds are roosting on the roof-top;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.33" xml:lang="en">The water laps at the foot of the hall.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.34" xml:lang="en">I through my thumb-ring into the river;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.35" xml:lang="en">I leave my girdle-gem in the bay of the Lǐ.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.36" xml:lang="en">35 Pollia I've plucked in the scent-laden islet</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.37" xml:lang="en">To give to the lady in the depths below.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.38" xml:lang="en">Time once gone cannot be recovered:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-6a.39" xml:lang="en">I wish I could play here a little longer.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.1" xml:lang="en">The Lady of the Xiāng</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.2" xml:lang="en">1 The child of God, descending the northern bank,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.3" xml:lang="en">Turns on me her eyes that are dark with longing.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.4" xml:lang="en">Gently the wind of autumn whispers;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.5" xml:lang="en">On the waves of the Dòng-tíng lake the leaves are falling.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.6" xml:lang="en">5 Over the white sedge I gaze out wildly;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.7" xml:lang="en">For a tryst is made to meet my love this evening.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.8" xml:lang="en">But why should the birds gather in the duckweed?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.9" xml:lang="en">And what are the nets doing in the tree-tops?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.10" xml:lang="en">The Yuán has its angelicas, the Lǐ has its orchids:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.11" xml:lang="en">10 And I think of my lady, but dare not tell it,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.12" xml:lang="en">As with trembling heart I gaze on the distance</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.13" xml:lang="en">Over the swiftly moving waters.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.14" xml:lang="en">What are the deer doing in the courtyard?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.15" xml:lang="en">Or the water-dragons outside the waters?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.16" xml:lang="en">15 In the morning I drive my steeds by the river;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.17" xml:lang="en">In the evening I cross to the western shore.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.18" xml:lang="en">I can hear my beloved calling to me:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.19" xml:lang="en">I will ride aloft and race beside her.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.20" xml:lang="en">I will build her a house within the water</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.21" xml:lang="en">20 Roofed all over with lotus leaves;</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.22" xml:lang="en">With walls of iris, of purple shells the chamber;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.23" xml:lang="en">Perfumed pepper shall make the hall.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.24" xml:lang="en">With beams of cassia, orchid rafters,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.25" xml:lang="en">Lily-tree lintel, a bower of peonies,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.26" xml:lang="en">25 With woven fig-leaves for the hangings</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.27" xml:lang="en">And melilotus to make a screen;</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.28" xml:lang="en">Weights of white jade to hold the mats with,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.29" xml:lang="en">Stone-orchids strewn to make the floor sweet:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.30" xml:lang="en">A room of lotus thatched with the white flag</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.31" xml:lang="en">30 Shall all be bound up with stalks of asarum.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.32" xml:lang="en">A thousand sweet flowers shall fill the courtyard,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.33" xml:lang="en">And rarest perfumes shall fill the gates.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.34" xml:lang="en">In hosts from their home on Doubting Mountain</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.35" xml:lang="en">Like clourds in number the spirits come thronging.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.36" xml:lang="en">35 I'll throw my thumb-ring into the river,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.37" xml:lang="en">Leave my girdle-gem in the bay of the Lǐ.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.38" xml:lang="en">Sweet pollia I've plucked in the little islet</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.39" xml:lang="en">To send to my far-away Beloved.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.40" xml:lang="en">Oh, rarely, rarely the time is given!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-8a.41" xml:lang="en">40 I wish I could play here a little longer.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-10a.1" xml:lang="en">The Great Master of Fate</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-10a.2" xml:lang="en">1 Open wide the door of heaven!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-10a.3" xml:lang="en">On a black cloud I ride in splendour,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-10a.4" xml:lang="en">Bidding the whirlwind drive before me,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-10a.5" xml:lang="en">Causing the rainstorm to lay the dust.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-10a.6" xml:lang="en">5 In sweeping circles my lord is descending:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-10a.7" xml:lang="en">'Let me follow you over the Kōng-sāng mountain!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-10a.8" xml:lang="en">See, the teeming peoples of the Nine Lands:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-10a.9" xml:lang="en">The span of their lives is in your hand!'</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-10a.10" xml:lang="en">Flying aloft, he soars serenely,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-10a.11" xml:lang="en">10 Riding the pure vapour, guiding yīn and yáng.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-10a.12" xml:lang="en">Speedily, lord, I will go with you,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-10a.13" xml:lang="en">Conducting High God to the height of heaven.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-10a.14" xml:lang="en">My cloud-coat hangs in billowing folds;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-10a.15" xml:lang="en">My jade girdle-pendants dangle low:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-10a.16" xml:lang="en">15 A yīn and a yáng, a yīn and a yáng:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-10a.17" xml:lang="en">None of the common folk know what I am doing.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-10a.18" xml:lang="en">I have plucked the glistening flower of the Holy Hemp</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-10a.19" xml:lang="en">To give to one who lives far away.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-10a.20" xml:lang="en">Old age already has crept upon me:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-10a.21" xml:lang="en">20 I am no longer near him, fast growing a stranger.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-10a.22" xml:lang="en">He drives his dragon chariot with thunder of wheels;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-10a.23" xml:lang="en">High up he rides, careering heavenwards.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-10a.24" xml:lang="en">But I stand where I am, twisting a spray of cassia:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-10a.25" xml:lang="en">The longing for him pains my heart.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-10a.26" xml:lang="en">25 It pains my heart, but what can I do?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-10a.27" xml:lang="en">If we only could stay as we were, unchanging!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-10a.28" xml:lang="en">But all man's life is fated;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-11a.1" xml:lang="en">Its meeting and partings not his to arrange.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-12a.1" xml:lang="en">The Lesser Master of Fate</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-12a.2" xml:lang="en">1 The autumn orchid and the deer-parsley</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-12a.3" xml:lang="en">Grow in a carpet below the hall;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-12a.4" xml:lang="en">The leaves of green and the pure white flowers</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-12a.5" xml:lang="en">Assail me with their wafted fragrance.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-12a.8" xml:lang="en">5 The autumn orchids bloom luxuriant,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-12a.9" xml:lang="en">With leaves of green and purple stems.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-12a.10" xml:lang="en">All the hall is filled with lovely women,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-12a.11" xml:lang="en">But his eyes swiftly sought me out from the rest.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-12a.12" xml:lang="en">Without a word he came in to me, without a word he left me:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-12a.13" xml:lang="en">10 He rode off on the whirlwind with cloud-banners flying.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-12a.14" xml:lang="en">No sorrow is greater than the parting of the living.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-12a.15" xml:lang="en">No happiness is greater than making new friendships.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-12a.16" xml:lang="en">Wearing a lotus coat with melilotus girdle,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-12a.17" xml:lang="en">Quickly he came and as quickly departed.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-12a.18" xml:lang="en">15 At night he will lodge in the High God's precincts.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-12a.19" xml:lang="en">'Whom are you waiting for at the cloud's edge?'</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-12a.22" xml:lang="en">I will wash my hair with you in the Pool of Heaven;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-12a.23" xml:lang="en">You shall dry your hair on the Bank of Sunlight.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-12a.24" xml:lang="en">I watch for the Fair One, but he does not come.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-12a.25" xml:lang="en">20 Wildly I shout my song into the wind.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-12a.26" xml:lang="en">With peacock canopy and kingfisher banner,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-12a.27" xml:lang="en">He mounts the ninefold heaven and grasps the Broom Star;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-12a.28" xml:lang="en">He brandishes his long sword, protecting young and old:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-12a.29" xml:lang="en">`You only, Fragrant One, are worthy to be judge over men.'</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-14a.1" xml:lang="en">The Lord of the East</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-14a.2" xml:lang="en">1 With a faint flush I start to come out of the east,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-14a.3" xml:lang="en">Shining down on my treshold, Fú-sāng. [balustrade]</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-14a.4" xml:lang="en">As I urge my horses slowly forwards,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-14a.5" xml:lang="en">The night sky brightens, and day has come.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-14a.6" xml:lang="en">5 I ride a dragon car and chariot on the thunder,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-14a.7" xml:lang="en">With cloud-banners fluttering upon the wind.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-14a.8" xml:lang="en">I heave a long sigh as I start the ascent,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-14a.9" xml:lang="en">Reluctant to leave, and looking back longingly;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-14a.10" xml:lang="en">For the beauty and the music are so enchanting,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-14a.11" xml:lang="en">10 The beholder, delighted, forgets that he must go.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-14a.12" xml:lang="en">Tighten the zither's strings and smithe them in unison!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-14a.13" xml:lang="en">Strike the bells until the bell-stand rocks!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-14a.14" xml:lang="en">Let the flutes sound! Blow the pan-pipes!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-14a.15" xml:lang="en">See the priestesses, how skilled and lovely,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-14a.16" xml:lang="en">15 Whirling and dipping like birds in flight,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-14a.17" xml:lang="en">Unfolding the words in time to the dancing,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-14a.18" xml:lang="en">Pitch and beat all in perfect accord!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-14a.19" xml:lang="en">The spirits, descending, darken the sun.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-14a.20" xml:lang="en">In my cloud-coat and my skirt of the rainbow,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-14a.21" xml:lang="en">20 Grasping my bow I soar high up in the sky.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-14a.22" xml:lang="en">I aim my long arrow and shoot the Wolf of Heaven;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-14a.23" xml:lang="en">I seize the Dipper to ladle cinnamon wine.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-14a.24" xml:lang="en">Then holding my reins, I plunge down to my setting,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-14a.25" xml:lang="en">On my gloomy night journey back to the east.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-16a.1" xml:lang="en">The River Earl</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-16a.2" xml:lang="en">1 I wander with you by the Nine Mouths of the river</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-16a.3" xml:lang="en">When the storm wind rises and lashes up the waves.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-16a.4" xml:lang="en">I ride a water chariot with a canopy of lotus;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-16a.5" xml:lang="en">Two dragons draw it, between two water-serpents.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-16a.6" xml:lang="en">5 I climb the Kūn-lún mountain and look over the four quarters,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-16a.7" xml:lang="en">And my heart leaps up in me, beating wildly.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-16a.8" xml:lang="en">Though the day will soon end, I forget to go in my pleasure:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-16a.9" xml:lang="en">Longingly I look back to that distant shore.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-16a.10" xml:lang="en">Of fish-scales his palace is, with a dragon-scale hall;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-16a.11" xml:lang="en">10 Purple cowrie gate-towers; rooms of pearl.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-16a.12" xml:lang="en">And what does the god do, down there in the water?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-16a.13" xml:lang="en">Riding a white turtle, he chases the spotted fishes.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-16a.14" xml:lang="en">Let me play with you among the river's islets,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-16a.15" xml:lang="en">While the swollen waters come rushing in on their way!</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-16a.16" xml:lang="en">15 Eastward you journey, with hands stately folded,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-16a.17" xml:lang="en">Bearing your fair bride to the southern harbour.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-16a.18" xml:lang="en">The waves come racing up to meet me,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-16a.19" xml:lang="en">And shoals of fishes are my bridal train.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-18a.1" xml:lang="en">The Mountain Spirit</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-18a.2" xml:lang="en">1 There seems to be someone in the fold of the mountain</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-18a.3" xml:lang="en">In a coat of fig-leaves with a rabbit-floss girdle,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-18a.4" xml:lang="en">With eyes that hold laugther and a smile of pearly brightness:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-18a.5" xml:lang="en">'Lady, your allurements show that you desire me.'</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-18a.6" xml:lang="en">5 Driving tawny leopards, leading the striped lynxes;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-18a.7" xml:lang="en">A car of lily-magnolia with banner of woven cassia:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-18a.8" xml:lang="en">Her cloak of stone-orchids, her belt of asarum:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-18a.9" xml:lang="en">She gathers sweet scents to give to the one she loves.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-18a.10" xml:lang="en">'I am in the dense bamboo grove, which never sees the sunlight,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-18a.11" xml:lang="en">10 So steep and hard the way was, therefore I am late.`</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-18a.12" xml:lang="en">Solitary she stands, upon the mountain's summit:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-18a.13" xml:lang="en">The clouds' dense masses begin below her.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-18a.14" xml:lang="en">From a place of gloomy shadow, dark even in the daytime,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-18a.15" xml:lang="en">When the east wind blows up, the goddess sends down her showers.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-18a.16" xml:lang="en">15 Dallying with the Fair One, I forget about returning.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-18a.17" xml:lang="en">What flowers can I deck myself with, so late in the year?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-18a.18" xml:lang="en">I shall pluck the thrice-flowering herb among the mountains,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-18a.19" xml:lang="en">Where the arrowroot spreads creeping over the piled-up boulders.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-18a.20" xml:lang="en">Sorrowing for my lady, I forget that I must go.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-18a.21" xml:lang="en">20 My lady thinks of me, but she has no time to come.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-18a.22" xml:lang="en">The lady of the mountains is fragrant with pollia;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-18a.23" xml:lang="en">She drinks from the rocky spring and shelters beneath the pine trees.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-18a.24" xml:lang="en">My lady thinks of me, but she holds back, uncertain.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-18a.25" xml:lang="en">The thunder rumbles; rain darkens the sky:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-18a.26" xml:lang="en">25 The monkeys chatter; apes scream in the night:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-18a.27" xml:lang="en">The wind soughs sadly and the trees rustle.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-18a.28" xml:lang="en">I think of my lady and stand alone in sadness.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-20a.1" xml:lang="en">Hymn to the Fallen</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-20a.2" xml:lang="en">1 Grasping our great shields and wearing our hide armour,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-20a.3" xml:lang="en">Wheel-hub to wheel-hub locked, we battle hand to hand.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-20a.4" xml:lang="en">Our banners darken the sky; the enemy teem like clouds:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-20a.5" xml:lang="en">Through the hail of arrows the warriors press forward.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-20a.6" xml:lang="en">5 They dash on our lines; they trample our ranks down.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-20a.7" xml:lang="en">The left horse has fallen, the right one is wounded.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-20a.8" xml:lang="en">The wheels are embedded, the foursome entangled:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-20a.9" xml:lang="en">Seize the jade drumstick and beat the sounding drum!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-20a.10" xml:lang="en">The time is against us: the gods are angry.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-20a.11" xml:lang="en">10 Now all lie dead, left on the field of battle.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-20a.12" xml:lang="en">They went out never more to return:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-20a.13" xml:lang="en">Far, far away they lie, on the level plain,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-20a.14" xml:lang="en">Their long swords at their belts, clasping their Qín bows,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-20a.15" xml:lang="en">Head from body sundered: but their hearts could not be vanquished.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-20a.16" xml:lang="en">15 Both truly brave and also truly noble;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-20a.17" xml:lang="en">Strong to the last, they could not be dishonored.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-20a.18" xml:lang="en">Their bodies may have died, but their souls are living:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-20a.19" xml:lang="en">Heroes among the shades their valiant souls will be.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-22a.1" xml:lang="en">Honouring the Dead</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-22a.2" xml:lang="en">The rites are accomplished to the beating of the drums;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-22a.3" xml:lang="en">The flower-wand is passed on to succeeding dancers.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-22a.4" xml:lang="en">Lovely maidens sing their song, slow and solemnly.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-22a.5" xml:lang="en">Orchids in spring and chrysantemums in autumn:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_002-22a.6" xml:lang="en">So it shall go on until the end of time.</seg>
</p>
<p>
</p>
</div>
<div><head>3 天問	Heavenly Questions</head>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.12" xml:lang="en">5 What manner of things</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.13" xml:lang="en">are the darkness and light?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.14" xml:lang="en">How did Yīn and Yáng come together,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.15" xml:lang="en">and how could they originate and transform all things that are by their commingling?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.16" xml:lang="en">7 Whose compass measured</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.17" xml:lang="en">out the ninefold heavens?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.18" xml:lang="en">Whose work was this,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.19" xml:lang="en">and how did he accomplish it?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.20" xml:lang="en">Where were the circling chords fastened,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.21" xml:lang="en">and where was the sky's pole fixed?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.22" xml:lang="en">Where did the Eight Pillars meet the sky,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.23" xml:lang="en">and why were they too short for it in the south-east?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.24" xml:lang="en">11 Where do the nine fields of heaven extend to</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.25" xml:lang="en">and where do they join each other?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.26" xml:lang="en">The ins and outs of their edges must be very many:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.27" xml:lang="en">who knows their number?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.28" xml:lang="en">13 How does heaven coordinate its motions?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.29" xml:lang="en">Where are the Twelve Houses divided?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.30" xml:lang="en">How do the sun and the moon hold to their courses</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.31" xml:lang="en">and the fixed stars keep their places?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.32" xml:lang="en">15 Setting out from the Gulf of Brightness</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.33" xml:lang="en">and going to rest in the Vale of Murk,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.34" xml:lang="en">from the dawn until the time of darkness,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.35" xml:lang="en">how many miles is the journey?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.36" xml:lang="en">17 What is the peculiar virtue of the moon, the Brightness of the Night,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.37" xml:lang="en">which causes it to grow once more after its death?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.38" xml:lang="en">Of what advantage is it</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.39" xml:lang="en">to keep a toad in its belly?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.40" xml:lang="en">19 How did the Mother Star get her nine children</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.41" xml:lang="en">without a union?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.42" xml:lang="en">Where is Lord Bluster, the Wind Star,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.43" xml:lang="en">and where does the warm wind live?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.44" xml:lang="en">21 What is it whose closing causes the dark</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.45" xml:lang="en">and whose opening causes the light?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-1a.46" xml:lang="en">Where does the Bright God hide</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.1" xml:lang="en">before the Horn proclaims the dawning of the day?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.2" xml:lang="en">23 If Gǔn was not fit to allay the flood,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.3" xml:lang="en">why was he given this charge?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.4" xml:lang="en">All said, 'Never fear!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.5" xml:lang="en">Try him out and see if he can do it.'</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.6" xml:lang="en">When the bird-turtles linked together,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.7" xml:lang="en">how did Gǔn follow their sign?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.8" xml:lang="en">And if he accomplished the work according to his will,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.9" xml:lang="en">why did the high lord punish him?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.10" xml:lang="en">Long he lay cast off on Feather Mountain:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.11" xml:lang="en">why for three whole years did he not rot?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.12" xml:lang="en">When Lord Gǔn brought forth Yǔ from his belly,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.13" xml:lang="en">how was he transformed?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.14" xml:lang="en">Yǔ inherited the same tradition</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.15" xml:lang="en">and carried on the work of his father.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.16" xml:lang="en">If he continued the work already begun,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.17" xml:lang="en">in what way was his plan a different one?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.18" xml:lang="en">How did he fill the flood waters up</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.19" xml:lang="en">where they were most deep?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.20" xml:lang="en">How did he set bounds</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.21" xml:lang="en">to the Nine Lands?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.22" xml:lang="en">What did the winged dragons trace on the ground?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.23" xml:lang="en">Where did the seas and rivers flow?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.24" xml:lang="en">33 What did Gǔn plan</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.25" xml:lang="en">and what did Yǔ accomplish?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.26" xml:lang="en">Why, when the Wicked One was enraged,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.27" xml:lang="en">did the earth sink down towards the south-east?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.28" xml:lang="en">Why are the lands of the earth dry</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.29" xml:lang="en">and the river valleys wet?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.30" xml:lang="en">They flow eastwards without ever getting exhausted:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.31" xml:lang="en">who knows the cause of this?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.32" xml:lang="en">What are the distances</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.33" xml:lang="en">from east to west and from north to south?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.34" xml:lang="en">From north to south the earth is longer and narrower.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.35" xml:lang="en">What is the difference between its length and breath?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.36" xml:lang="en">Where is Kūn-lún</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.37" xml:lang="en">with its Hanging Garden?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.38" xml:lang="en">How many miles high</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.39" xml:lang="en">are its ninefold walls?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.40" xml:lang="en">Who goes through</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.41" xml:lang="en">the gates in its four sides?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-2a.42" xml:lang="en">When the north-east one opens,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-3a.1" xml:lang="en">what wind is it that passes through?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-3a.2" xml:lang="en">What land does the sun not shine on</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-3a.3" xml:lang="en">and how does the Torch Dragon light it?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-3a.4" xml:lang="en">Why are the Ruò flowers bright</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-3a.5" xml:lang="en">before Xī Hé is stirring?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-3a.6" xml:lang="en">What place is warm in winter?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-3a.7" xml:lang="en">What place is cold in summer?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-3a.8" xml:lang="en">Where is the stone forest?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-3a.9" xml:lang="en">What beast can talk?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-3a.10" xml:lang="en">Where are the hornless dragons</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-3a.11" xml:lang="en">which carry bears on their beaks for sport?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-3a.12" xml:lang="en">Where is the great serpent with nine heads</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-3a.13" xml:lang="en">and where is Shū Hū?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-3a.14" xml:lang="en">Where is it that people do not age?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-3a.15" xml:lang="en">Where do giants live?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-3a.16" xml:lang="en">Where is the nine-branched weed?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-3a.17" xml:lang="en">Where is the floower of the Great Hemp?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-3a.18" xml:lang="en">How does the snake that can swallow an elephant</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-3a.19" xml:lang="en">digest its bones?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-3a.20" xml:lang="en">Where is the Black Water that dyes the feet,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-3a.21" xml:lang="en">and where is the Mountain of Three Perils?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-3a.22" xml:lang="en">The folk there put death off for many years:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-3a.23" xml:lang="en">what is the limmit of their age?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-3a.24" xml:lang="en">Where does the man-fish live?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.1" xml:lang="en">Where is the Monster Bird?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.2" xml:lang="en">56 When Yì shot down the suns,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.3" xml:lang="en">why did the ravens shed their feathers?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.4" xml:lang="en">57 Yǔ4 laboured with all his might.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.5" xml:lang="en">He came down and looked on the earth below.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.6" xml:lang="en">How did he get that maid of Tú-shān</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.7" xml:lang="en">and lie with her in Tái-sāng?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.8" xml:lang="en">The lady became his mate</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.9" xml:lang="en">and her body had issue.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.10" xml:lang="en">How came they to have appetite for the same dish</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.11" xml:lang="en">when they sated their hunger with the morning food of love?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.12" xml:lang="en">61 Qǐ supplanted Yì and made himself lord</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.13" xml:lang="en">but later met with mishap.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.14" xml:lang="en">How did Qǐ fall into trouble,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.15" xml:lang="en">and how did he succeed in warding it off?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.16" xml:lang="en">and did no harm to his person.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.17" xml:lang="en">How is it that Yì lost lordship</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.18" xml:lang="en">and Yǔ's seed was continued?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.19" xml:lang="en">Qǐ was many times the guest of God in heaven</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.20" xml:lang="en">and brought back the Nine Changes and the Nine Songs.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.21" xml:lang="en">Why, if he was so good a son, did he kill his mother,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.22" xml:lang="en">and why were his lands divided up after his death?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.23" xml:lang="en">67 God sent down Lord Yì</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.24" xml:lang="en">to overcome the calamities of the people below.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.25" xml:lang="en">Why then did he shoot the River Lord</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.26" xml:lang="en">and take to wife that Lady of the Luò?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.27" xml:lang="en">With his trusty bow and good thumb-ring</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.28" xml:lang="en">he shot the Great Swine.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.29" xml:lang="en">Why, when he offered the fat of its flesh cooked as a sacrifice,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.30" xml:lang="en">was the Lord God displeased?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.31" xml:lang="en">Zhuó took the Black Fox to wife,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.32" xml:lang="en">and that Dark woman plotted with him.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.33" xml:lang="en">How was Yì's body boiled,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.34" xml:lang="en">and how did they conspire to have him eaten?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.35" xml:lang="en">73 On that westward journey from Zǔ to Qióng-shi(?)</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.36" xml:lang="en">how did Yì cross the heights?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.37" xml:lang="en">And when Gǔn turned into a brown bear,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.38" xml:lang="en">how did the shamans bring him back to life?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.39" xml:lang="en">Both sowed the black millet,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.40" xml:lang="en">and the rushlands became a place of husbandry.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.41" xml:lang="en">Why, if each made the same sowing,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.42" xml:lang="en">did Gǔn alone reap a harvest of infamy?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.43" xml:lang="en">77 What is the halo of white light</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.44" xml:lang="en">doing in this hall?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.45" xml:lang="en">Where did Yì get that goodly herb,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.46" xml:lang="en">and why could he not keep it?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.47" xml:lang="en">The heaven-made pattern embraces all,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.48" xml:lang="en">and when the yáng-spirit leaves, death ensues.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.49" xml:lang="en">Why did the great birds cry?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.50" xml:lang="en">How did they loose their substance?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.51" xml:lang="en">ī When Ping(?) summons up the rain,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.52" xml:lang="en">how does he raise it?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.53" xml:lang="en">When those different parts were assembled and joined on to a deer,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.54" xml:lang="en">how were they fitted into shape?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.55" xml:lang="en">ǐ When the Great Turtle walks along with an island on his back,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.56" xml:lang="en">how does he keep it steady?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.57" xml:lang="en">When the Strong Man made the boat move over dry land,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.58" xml:lang="en">how did he lift it?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.59" xml:lang="en">When Jiāo was in Hù,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.60" xml:lang="en">what did he want with his sister-in-law?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.61" xml:lang="en">How did Shào Kāng go hunting with his dogs</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.62" xml:lang="en">and bring his head tumbling down?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.63" xml:lang="en">Nǚ Qí sewed Jiāo's lower garment for him,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.64" xml:lang="en">and he lodged with her in her house.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.65" xml:lang="en">How did her head fall from her body</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.66" xml:lang="en">and she herself meet the end that was meant for him?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.67" xml:lang="en">When the Strong Man prepared his warriors for battle,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.68" xml:lang="en">with what did he strengthen them?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.69" xml:lang="en">When he overturned the boat of the Lord of Zhēn-xún,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.70" xml:lang="en">by what means did he take it?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.71" xml:lang="en">91 What did Jié get</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.72" xml:lang="en">when he attacked Měng-shān?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-4a.73" xml:lang="en">How did Mò Xī bewitch him,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.1" xml:lang="en">and how did Tāng kill him?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.2" xml:lang="en">93 If Shùn had a wife in his house,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.3" xml:lang="en">how could he be a barchelor?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.4" xml:lang="en">How could Yáo's two daughters be married to him</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.5" xml:lang="en">if he did not tell his family?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.6" xml:lang="en">-</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.7" xml:lang="en">-</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.8" xml:lang="en">95 Who built the ten-storeyed tower of jade?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.9" xml:lang="en">Who foresaw it all in the beginning, when the first signs appeared?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.10" xml:lang="en">By what law was Nǔ Wā</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.11" xml:lang="en">raised up to become high lord?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.12" xml:lang="en">By what means</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.13" xml:lang="en">did she fashion the different creatures?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.14" xml:lang="en">99 Shun served his brother,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.15" xml:lang="en">but his brother still did him evil.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.16" xml:lang="en">Why, when he behaved worse than a brute beast to Shùn,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.17" xml:lang="en">did Shùn's brother come to no harm?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.18" xml:lang="en">101 Fleeing from Gǔ Gōng(?), they posessed Wú</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.19" xml:lang="en">and stayed in Nán-yuè.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.20" xml:lang="en">Who would have thought to find the two princes</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.21" xml:lang="en">in that place?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.22" xml:lang="en">103 From a bird-shaped vessel embellished with jade</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.23" xml:lang="en">the high lord was feasted.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.24" xml:lang="en">How did he recieve counsel for Jié of Xià's overthrow,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.25" xml:lang="en">so that at the last he destroyed him?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.26" xml:lang="en">The high lord came down and looked about,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.27" xml:lang="en">and there he met Yī Zhì.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.28" xml:lang="en">How did he bring back Jié's chastisement,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.29" xml:lang="en">so that the people were mightily rejoiced?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.30" xml:lang="en">107 When Jiǎn Dí was in the tower,how did Kù favour her?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.31" xml:lang="en">When the swallow brought his gift, why was the maiden glad?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.32" xml:lang="en">109 Hai(?) inherited Jì's prowess.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.33" xml:lang="en">His father was a goodly man.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.34" xml:lang="en">Why did he end by loosing his oxen and sheep</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.35" xml:lang="en">in Yǒu-yi(?)</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.36" xml:lang="en">How did he win her heart</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.37" xml:lang="en">by dancing with shield and plumes,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.38" xml:lang="en">and how did she of the smooth sides and lovely skin</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.39" xml:lang="en">become his paramour?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.40" xml:lang="en">What did Yǒu-yi(?)'s herdsmen say</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.41" xml:lang="en">when they found them?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.42" xml:lang="en">When they struck the bed, he had already left the chamber:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.43" xml:lang="en">how did he meet his fate?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.44" xml:lang="en">Héng, too, inherited Jì's prowess.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.45" xml:lang="en">How did he get back those oxherds and oxen?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.46" xml:lang="en">How did he go about there dispensing gifts,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.47" xml:lang="en">but not return empty-handed?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.48" xml:lang="en">Dark Wēi followed in his brother's footsteps</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.49" xml:lang="en">and the Lord of Yǒu-yi(?) was stirred against him.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.50" xml:lang="en">Why, when the birds flocked together,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.51" xml:lang="en">did she forsake her own son and give herself to him?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.52" xml:lang="en">The Dark Man lay with her adulterously</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.53" xml:lang="en">and destroyed his elder brother.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.54" xml:lang="en">Why, after so much falsehood and treachery,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.55" xml:lang="en">was it given to his posterity to flourish?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.56" xml:lang="en">121 Tāng the Successful travelled to the east</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.57" xml:lang="en">and came to Yǒu-xīn.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.58" xml:lang="en">How did he come to ask for that bondsman</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.59" xml:lang="en">and win a goodly queen?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.60" xml:lang="en">From the tree by the water's edge</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.61" xml:lang="en">they got that little child.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.62" xml:lang="en">Why did they so hate him</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.63" xml:lang="en">that they sent him away with the lady of Yǒu-xīn?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.64" xml:lang="en">Tāng came out of Chóng-quán:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.65" xml:lang="en">for what crime was he shut up there?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-5a.66" xml:lang="en">Who provoked him to march</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.1" xml:lang="en">with impatient heart against his lord king?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.2" xml:lang="en">127 On the morning of the first day we took our oath.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.3" xml:lang="en">How did we all arrive on time?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.4" xml:lang="en">When the grey geese came flocking together,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.5" xml:lang="en">at whose summons did they gather?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.6" xml:lang="en">When Zhòu's body was beheaded and mutilated,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.7" xml:lang="en">why was Shū Dàn unhappy?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.8" xml:lang="en">When on his own he planned</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.10" xml:lang="en">to make the dominion of Zhōu secure, why did King Fā sigh?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.11" xml:lang="en">For what kingly virtue</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.12" xml:lang="en">did Heaven bestow Yīn's empire on him,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.13" xml:lang="en">and for what sin was it taken from him</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.14" xml:lang="en">so soon after he had achieved it?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.15" xml:lang="en">How were the princes able to make rebellion</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.16" xml:lang="en">when all the weapons of war were handed in?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.17" xml:lang="en">And how did Shū Dàn lead his armies</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.18" xml:lang="en">to smithe them on both their flanks?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.19" xml:lang="en">135 Lord Zhāo did much travelling.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.20" xml:lang="en">What did it profit him</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.21" xml:lang="en">to meet that white rhinoceros</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.22" xml:lang="en">when he went to the South Land?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.23" xml:lang="en">137 King Mù was a breeder of horses.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.24" xml:lang="en">For what reason did he roam about?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.25" xml:lang="en">What was he looking for</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.26" xml:lang="en">when he made his circuit of the earth?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.27" xml:lang="en">139 When the witches were tied up together,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.28" xml:lang="en">what was it that was crying in the market-place?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.29" xml:lang="en">Whom was Yōu of Zhōu punishing</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.30" xml:lang="en">when he got that Bāo Sì?　[and how did he?CH]</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.31" xml:lang="en">Heaven in its dispensations veers first to one side and then to the other.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.32" xml:lang="en">Why did it first favour him and then afterwards punish him?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.33" xml:lang="en">141 Huán of Qí nine times assembled the vassals</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.34" xml:lang="en">yet in the end his body was destroyed.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.35" xml:lang="en">143 Who was it that led</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.36" xml:lang="en">King Zhòu into folly?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.37" xml:lang="en">Why did he hate his ministers</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.38" xml:lang="en">and let flatterers and backbiters serve him?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.39" xml:lang="en">How had Bǐ Gān offended</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.40" xml:lang="en">that he should be suppressed,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.41" xml:lang="en">and how had Léi Kaī found favour</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.42" xml:lang="en">to be given a fief?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.43" xml:lang="en">Why is it that wise men whose virtue is the same yet act in different ways?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.44" xml:lang="en">Méi Bó was sliced and salted,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.45" xml:lang="en">but Jī Zǐ feigned madness.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.46" xml:lang="en">149 King Millet was his first born:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.47" xml:lang="en">why did the high lord treat him so cruelly?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.48" xml:lang="en">When he was left out on the ice,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.49" xml:lang="en">how did the birds keep him warm?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.50" xml:lang="en">Drawing his bow to the full and grasping the arrow,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.51" xml:lang="en">how did he become a war-leader?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.52" xml:lang="en">After giving the high lord so great a shock,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.53" xml:lang="en">how did he come to have a glorious future?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.54" xml:lang="en">153 Lord Chāng abandoned his own title</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.55" xml:lang="en">and consented to be a sheperd of the marshes for King Zhòu.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.56" xml:lang="en">Why then did he remove his altars from Qí</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.57" xml:lang="en">and claim heaven's mandate to supplant Yīn?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.58" xml:lang="en">155 When Tai packed up his posessions and moved to Qí,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.59" xml:lang="en">how did he get the people to follow him?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.60" xml:lang="en">Yīn had a woman of guile:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.61" xml:lang="en">what protests did he hear?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.62" xml:lang="en">157 When Zhòu bestowed that flesh on him,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.63" xml:lang="en">the Lord of the West declared it to heaven.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.64" xml:lang="en">Why did Zhòu invite God's chastisement,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.65" xml:lang="en">so that the dominion of Yīn could not be saved?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.66" xml:lang="en">159 When Wàng the Counsellor was in the market,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.67" xml:lang="en">how did Chāng know him?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.68" xml:lang="en">When he struck with his knife and the sound rang out,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.69" xml:lang="en">why was the king pleased?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.70" xml:lang="en">161 When Wǔ set out to kill Yīn,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.71" xml:lang="en">why was he grieved?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.72" xml:lang="en">He went into battle carrying his father's corpse:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.73" xml:lang="en">why was he in such a hurry?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.74" xml:lang="en">163 Why did Bó Lín hang himself?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.76" xml:lang="en">When heaven was moved by his death to afflict the earth,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.77" xml:lang="en">who was so afraid?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.78" xml:lang="en">165 When High God in heaven confers his mandate,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.79" xml:lang="en">how does He give notice of it?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.80" xml:lang="en">When He has bestowed dominion over the world on one,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.81" xml:lang="en">why does He take it away and give it to another?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.82" xml:lang="en">167 At first Táng made Zhì his servant,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.83" xml:lang="en">but afterwards he made him his counsellor.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.84" xml:lang="en">How did Zhì end by becoming Táng's minister,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.85" xml:lang="en">and after his death share in the sacrifices of the royal ancestors?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.86" xml:lang="en">169 Hé the Valiant was the grandson of Mèng.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.87" xml:lang="en">When he was young he was an outcast.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.88" xml:lang="en">How did he make strong his might,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.89" xml:lang="en">so that he could spread his authority abroad?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.90" xml:lang="en">171 What happened when Péng Kēng</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.91" xml:lang="en">offered the pheasant's broth to the high lord?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.92" xml:lang="en">After enjoying so long a life,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.93" xml:lang="en">why did he still have regrets?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.94" xml:lang="en">173 When the lords of the centre ruled together,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.95" xml:lang="en">why was the lord king angry?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.96" xml:lang="en">Wasps and ants have a mean fate:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.97" xml:lang="en">how could their power be enduring?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.98" xml:lang="en">175 When the maiden warned the brothers not to pick ferns,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.99" xml:lang="en">how did the deer come to their aid?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.100" xml:lang="en">When they came north to the whirling water,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.101" xml:lang="en">why were they glad to be in that place?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.102" xml:lang="en">177 The elder brother had a hunting-dog.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.103" xml:lang="en">Why did the younger brother desire it?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.104" xml:lang="en">The elder brother bestowed a hundred chariots on him,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-6a.105" xml:lang="en">yet he ended by losing all his substance.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-7a.2" xml:lang="en">179 Towards evening there was thunder and lightning.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-7a.3" xml:lang="en">why was the lady sad?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-7a.4" xml:lang="en">The high lord did not reveal his majesty.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-7a.5" xml:lang="en">What was he seeking?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-7a.6" xml:lang="en">1ī What was the king's sorrow</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-7a.7" xml:lang="en">when he lay in hiding and lived in caves?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-7a.10" xml:lang="en">when he awoke to the error of his ways?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-7a.11" xml:lang="en">What did we say [transposed] [[[When Jīng was glorious in war, how came we to be the leaders?]]]</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-7a.12" xml:lang="en">But when Guāng of Wú seized power,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-7a.13" xml:lang="en">why were we so long defeated?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-7a.14" xml:lang="en">185 Round the village they went and through the altars until they came to the holy mounds.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-7a.15" xml:lang="en">How came Zǐ Wén to be the fruit of such wantonness?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-7a.16" xml:lang="en">186 ...Dū Āo did not reign for long. How is it that though he murdered his lord</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-7a.17" xml:lang="en">and seized kingship for himself,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_003-7a.18" xml:lang="en">yet the fame of his loyalty spread throughout the world?</seg>
</p>
<p>
</p>
</div>
<div><head>4 九章</head>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-2a.1" xml:lang="en">Grieving I make my plaint</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-2a.2" xml:lang="en">1 Grieving I make my plaint, to give my sorrows rein,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-2a.3" xml:lang="en">To vent my wrath and tell my pent-up thoughts.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-2a.4" xml:lang="en">If what I say is not in honesty,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-2a.5" xml:lang="en">I call on Heaven above to testify;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-2a.6" xml:lang="en">I bid the Five Lords to come and judge between us;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-2a.7" xml:lang="en">I summon the Six to appear with me in witness;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-2a.8" xml:lang="en">The spirits of mountain and river I'll cause to support my suit;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-2a.9" xml:lang="en">And Gāo Yáo shall hear my words and judge wether they are true.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-2a.10" xml:lang="en">9 I served my prince with all of my devotion,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-2a.11" xml:lang="en">Yet I was cast out from the rest like an unwanted wen.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-2a.12" xml:lang="en">I forgot to fawn and simper; I turned my back on the crowd,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-2a.13" xml:lang="en">Awaiting my prince in his wisdom to know the true from the false;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-2a.14" xml:lang="en">For my words and my deeds followed one in the steps of the other,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-2a.15" xml:lang="en">And that which I felt and that which I showed, between them there was no change.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-2a.16" xml:lang="en">Who better can judge a man than the prince he serves?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-2a.17" xml:lang="en">For to test him he has not far to seek for proofs.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-2a.18" xml:lang="en">17 My loyalty put my prince first and my own life after;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-2a.19" xml:lang="en">And because of this, I earned the crowd's enmity.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-2a.20" xml:lang="en">I thought of my prince alone, and of no other;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-2a.21" xml:lang="en">And that, too, was a thing that the mob abhorred.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-2a.22" xml:lang="en">But I see that to serve with all one's heart, careless of all things else,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-2a.23" xml:lang="en">Is a way that holds little promise that a man may be secure;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-2a.24" xml:lang="en">And a recless devotion to a prince, with no thought for any other,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-2a.25" xml:lang="en">Is a road whereby he may easily court disaster.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-3a.2" xml:lang="en">25 There is no one who in his thoughts have been more loyal to his prince:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-3a.3" xml:lang="en">Forgetful of lowly rank and poverty.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-3a.4" xml:lang="en">In serving my prince with an undivided heart</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-3a.5" xml:lang="en">My mind vas obsessed; I knew not the door to his favours.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-3a.6" xml:lang="en">What crime was my loyalty, that it should be thus punished?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-3a.7" xml:lang="en">Sure, this was not the return that in my heart I looked for.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-3a.8" xml:lang="en">I walked not with the rest, and when I fell</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-3a.9" xml:lang="en">My fall gave cause to the crowd for merriment.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-3a.10" xml:lang="en">33 I was charged with many crimes; I met with many a slander;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-3a.11" xml:lang="en">Caught in a mesh that I knew not how to untie.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-3a.12" xml:lang="en">My feelings were stifled and could not find expression,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-3a.13" xml:lang="en">For they screened me from my lord, that I might not explain myself.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-3a.14" xml:lang="en">Heavy with sorrow, I waited irresolutely;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-3a.15" xml:lang="en">But none cared to examine what lay within my heart.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-3a.16" xml:lang="en">I could not collect my disordered words to present him;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-3a.17" xml:lang="en">I wished to set forth my mind, but there was no way.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-3a.18" xml:lang="en">41 If I left and retired into silence, then no one could ever know;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-3a.19" xml:lang="en">And if I went in and shouted, still no one would hear my cries.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-3a.20" xml:lang="en">I stood for a long time waiting, sore perplexed by the quandary,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-3a.21" xml:lang="en">And my mind was wexed and troubled with many sorrows.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-4a.2" xml:lang="en">41 Once I dreamt that I climbed up to the heavens,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-4a.3" xml:lang="en">But when my soul had reached half-way, it could go no farther.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-4a.4" xml:lang="en">I summoned the God of Plague to interpret it for me:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-4a.5" xml:lang="en">He said, 'Your ambition aspires, but will find no helpers;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-4a.6" xml:lang="en">And in the end you face peril alone, cut off from other men.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-4a.7" xml:lang="en">You may think of none but your prince, but you should not rely on him,'</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-4a.8" xml:lang="en">51 It is true that 'many tounges can make metal molten':</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-4a.9" xml:lang="en">Pure metal was I at first, and yet I have come to this pass.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-4a.10" xml:lang="en">'He that was burned by broth will afterwards blow on pickles':</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-4a.11" xml:lang="en">Why then should I not alter my high intent?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-4a.12" xml:lang="en">I have cast down the ladder, but still I would mount to heaven:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-4a.13" xml:lang="en">My plight is the same as it was that time in my dream.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-4a.14" xml:lang="en">57 The crowd are frightened and turn their hearts against me;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-4a.15" xml:lang="en">How can I make companions of such as these?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-4a.16" xml:lang="en">Our end is the same, but the paths we thread are different.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-4a.17" xml:lang="en">How can I look to such as these to guide me?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-4a.18" xml:lang="en">Shēn Shēng of Jìn was a son most filial;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-4a.19" xml:lang="en">Yet his father gave ear to slander and loved him not.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-4a.20" xml:lang="en">Stiff-necked in all his ways and recking nothing,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-4a.21" xml:lang="en">Gǔn's work, because of this, had no prosperous conclusion.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-5a.2" xml:lang="en">65 I once heard it said that he wo acts loyally wins hatred for his pains,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-5a.3" xml:lang="en">And at that time I lightly said that the saying was a false one.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-5a.4" xml:lang="en">But 'he who has nine times broken his arm may set up as a physician';</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-5a.5" xml:lang="en">And now at last I know that what I was told is true.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-5a.6" xml:lang="en">The crossbow was set and waiting overhead,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-5a.7" xml:lang="en">And the bird-nets spread out ready down below,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-5a.8" xml:lang="en">And all was set, and the traps laid out to gratify my lord,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-5a.9" xml:lang="en">So that even if I wished to escape, there was no way to turn.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-5a.10" xml:lang="en">73 If I thought to tarry where I was and asked that I might stay,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-5a.11" xml:lang="en">I feared that a heavier fate might fall and he find more faults in me.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-5a.12" xml:lang="en">If I thought to fly up high and settle far off elsewhere,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-5a.13" xml:lang="en">My lord would, feigning, ask me, 'Where will you go?'</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-5a.14" xml:lang="en">I might seek to pursue a crooked path and leave the straight road behind,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-5a.15" xml:lang="en">But my will was too strong and would not allow me to.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-5a.16" xml:lang="en">My back and my breast are split like a tally and my heart, torn between them, aches,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-5a.17" xml:lang="en">And my mind is gloomed and perplexed in a skein of care.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-5a.18" xml:lang="en">ī I have pounded magnolia and mixed it with orchids,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-5a.19" xml:lang="en">And ground up pepper flowers to make my provender;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-5a.20" xml:lang="en">I have sown gracillary and planted chrysantemums</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-5a.21" xml:lang="en">To serve when the spring days come as savours for my food.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-5a.22" xml:lang="en">And because I fear that my true intent will not be believed,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-5a.23" xml:lang="en">I have rehearsed all here to make myself understood.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-5a.24" xml:lang="en">I wish only to speed away and remove myself far off,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-5a.25" xml:lang="en">To cherish these my delights in a private place.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-7a.1" xml:lang="en">Crossing the River</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-7a.2" xml:lang="en">1 When I was young I loved this rare apparel;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-7a.3" xml:lang="en">And now I am old in years, the passion has not abated:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-7a.4" xml:lang="en">At my belt a long sword swinging,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-7a.5" xml:lang="en">On my head a 'cleave-cloud' hat up-towering,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-7a.6" xml:lang="en">5 Round my neck moon-bright jewels, and a precious jade at my girdle.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-7a.7" xml:lang="en">But the world was muddy-witted and could not understand me,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-7a.8" xml:lang="en">And so I rode high and would not look back on it.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-7a.9" xml:lang="en">With a team of azure dragons, white serpents in the traces,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-7a.10" xml:lang="en">I rode with Chóng Huā in the Garden of Jasper,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-7a.11" xml:lang="en">10 Climbed mount Kūn-lún and ate of the flower of jade,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-7a.12" xml:lang="en">And won long life, lasting as heaven and earth;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-7a.13" xml:lang="en">And the sun and the moon were not more bright than I.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-7a.14" xml:lang="en">13 I was sad that the southern tribesmen could not undestand me,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-7a.15" xml:lang="en">For at dawn I had to cross the Jiāng and the Xiāng.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-8a.2" xml:lang="en">15 Climbing the height at Èzhǔ I looked back:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-8a.3" xml:lang="en">Ah! the last breath of autumn and winter's chill!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-8a.4" xml:lang="en">I walked my horses along the mountain side;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-8a.5" xml:lang="en">I drove my chariot towards Fāng-lín;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-8a.6" xml:lang="en">Then, boarding a barge, I sailed up the River Yuán.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-8a.7" xml:lang="en">20 The oars of Wú dipped in time and beat the billowing water.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-8a.8" xml:lang="en">The boat went slowly, making little headway:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-8a.9" xml:lang="en">Held by the whirling water she stuck fast.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-8a.10" xml:lang="en">That morning we put off from Wǎng-zhǔ;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-8a.11" xml:lang="en">The night we spent at Chén-yáng.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-8a.12" xml:lang="en">25 - If only my heart is straight and true,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-8a.13" xml:lang="en">What matters it how remote my abode? -</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-9a.2" xml:lang="en">When we entered Xù-pú, I halted uncertainly,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-9a.3" xml:lang="en">Too distraught to think where I was going.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-9a.4" xml:lang="en">Amid the deep woods there, in the twilight gloom,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-9a.5" xml:lang="en">30 Are the haunts where monkeys live.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-9a.6" xml:lang="en">The mountains' awful height screens the noonday sun,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-9a.7" xml:lang="en">And below it is dark and dim with perpetual r ain;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-9a.8" xml:lang="en">Sleet and snow fall there unendingly,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-9a.9" xml:lang="en">And the heavy clouds begin where the rooftops end.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-9a.10" xml:lang="en">35 Alas, that my life should be so devoid of pleasure!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-9a.11" xml:lang="en">That I should live here, alone and obscure, among the mountains!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-9a.12" xml:lang="en">But I cannot change my heart and follow the vulgar crowd,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-9a.13" xml:lang="en">And so I must face bitter sorrow and a hopeless end as my lot.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-10a.2" xml:lang="en">Jiē Yú shaved his head;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-10a.3" xml:lang="en">40 Sāng Hù naked ran;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-10a.4" xml:lang="en">So a loyal man is not certain to be used,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-10a.5" xml:lang="en">Nor a wise man certain to be employed.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-10a.6" xml:lang="en">Wǔ Zǐ-xu(?) met a bad end;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-10a.7" xml:lang="en">Bǐ Gān was cut and made into pickles.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-10a.8" xml:lang="en">45 In former times it was always like this;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-10a.9" xml:lang="en">Why should I complain of the men of today?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-10a.10" xml:lang="en">I shall make my path straight, with no fear of the rest;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-11a.1" xml:lang="en">For my days are sure to end in dark confusion.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-11a.2" xml:lang="en">LUAN</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-11a.3" xml:lang="en">The phoenix and the phoenix's mate are daily more and more remote,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-11a.4" xml:lang="en">50 And swallows, sparrows, crows and pies nest in the chambers and the high halls.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-11a.5" xml:lang="en">The daphne and lily-magnola die in the wild wood's tangle;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-11a.6" xml:lang="en">Stinking weeds find a position: fragrant flowers may not come near.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-11a.7" xml:lang="en">For the Dark and Light have changed places: the times are out fo joint.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-11a.8" xml:lang="en">With true heart long I pondered;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-12a.1" xml:lang="en">then suddenly I set forth.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-13a.1" xml:lang="en">A Lament for Ying</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-13a.2" xml:lang="en">1 High Heaven is not constant in its dispensations:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-13a.3" xml:lang="en">See how the country is moved to unrest and error!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-13a.4" xml:lang="en">The people are scattered and men cut off from their fellows.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-13a.5" xml:lang="en">In the middle of spring the move to the east began.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-13a.6" xml:lang="en">I left my old home and set off for distant places,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-13a.7" xml:lang="en">And following the waters of the Jiāng and the Xià, I travelled into exile.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-13a.8" xml:lang="en">I passed through the gate of Chǔ with a heavy heart:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-13a.9" xml:lang="en">On the day jiǎ, in the morning, my journey began.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-13a.10" xml:lang="en">9 As I set out from Yǐng and left my old ward in the city,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-13a.11" xml:lang="en">An endless turmoil started in my mind.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-13a.12" xml:lang="en">And as the oars slowly swept in time,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-13a.13" xml:lang="en">'Oh my Yǐng, I shall never look on you again!'</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-13a.14" xml:lang="en">I gazed on the high catalpa trees and heaved a heavy sigh,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-13a.15" xml:lang="en">And the tears in torrents, like winter's sleet, came down.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-13a.16" xml:lang="en">We passed the head of the Xià; and once, when we drifted westwards,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-13a.17" xml:lang="en">I looked back for the Dragon Gate, but I could not see it.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-13a.18" xml:lang="en">17 My mind was drawn with yearning and my heart was grieved.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-13a.19" xml:lang="en">So far! I knew not wither my way was leading,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-13a.20" xml:lang="en">But followed the wind and waves, drifting on aimlessly,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-13a.21" xml:lang="en">A traveller on an endless journey, with no hope of return.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-13a.22" xml:lang="en">As we rode on the Wave God's surging swell,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-13a.23" xml:lang="en">Oh when, I thought, will this aimless wandering cease?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-13a.24" xml:lang="en">My heart was caught in a mesh that I could not disentangle;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-13a.25" xml:lang="en">My thoughts were lost in a maze there was no way out of.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-13a.26" xml:lang="en">25 I let my boat float on, following the current downstream,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-13a.27" xml:lang="en">South up to the Dòng-tíng lake, and then north again to the River.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-13a.28" xml:lang="en">I had left behind the home where I dwelt so long,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-13a.29" xml:lang="en">And now, at random drifting, I travelled towards the east.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-14a.2" xml:lang="en">But my soul within me longed to be returning:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-14a.3" xml:lang="en">Ah! when for one moment of the day have I not longed to go back?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-14a.4" xml:lang="en">I turned my back on Xià-pǔ, and my thoughts went speeding westwards,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-14a.5" xml:lang="en">And I grieved that the Old City grew daily farther from me.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-14a.6" xml:lang="en">33 I climbed a steep islet's height and looked into the distance,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-14a.7" xml:lang="en">Thinking to ease the sorrow in my heart:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-14a.8" xml:lang="en">But only grief came for the rich, blest River Kingdom,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-14a.9" xml:lang="en">For its cherished ways, now lost beyond recall.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-14a.10" xml:lang="en">I may not traverse the surging waters to return there,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-14a.11" xml:lang="en">Or cross south over the vatery waste to reach it.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-14a.12" xml:lang="en">To think that its palace walls should be mounds of rubble,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-14a.13" xml:lang="en">And its two East Gates a wilderness of weeds!</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-14a.14" xml:lang="en">41 It is now a long time since my heart has known happiness;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-14a.15" xml:lang="en">Grief comes following sorrow and sorrow following grief.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-14a.16" xml:lang="en">I think how long and hard the road to Yǐng is,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-14a.17" xml:lang="en">And the River and the Xià how hard for me to cross,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-14a.18" xml:lang="en">Sometimes it seems but a night or two since I left it;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-14a.19" xml:lang="en">Yet now I have been here nine years without returning.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-14a.20" xml:lang="en">I am overcast with a sadness which cannot find expression;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-15a.1" xml:lang="en">I am tied to one spot and my mouth is full of gall.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-15a.2" xml:lang="en">49 When your favour was courted with outward show of charm,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-15a.3" xml:lang="en">You were too weak; you had no will of your own.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-15a.4" xml:lang="en">But then, with deep loyalty, I tried to go in before you,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-15a.5" xml:lang="en">Jealousy cut me off and blocked my way to you.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-15a.6" xml:lang="en">53 Though Yáo and Shùn exelled in noble actions,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-15a.7" xml:lang="en">So that their glory reaches to the skies,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-15a.8" xml:lang="en">The crowd of backbiters were envious of their fame</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-15a.9" xml:lang="en">And gave them a false name, saying they were not kind.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-15a.10" xml:lang="en">57 You hate the deep and studious search for beauty,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-15a.11" xml:lang="en">But love a base knave's braggart blusterings;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-15a.12" xml:lang="en">And so the crowd press forward and each day advance in your favours,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-15a.13" xml:lang="en">And true beauty is forced far off, and retires to distant places.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-16a.2" xml:lang="en">LUAN</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-16a.3" xml:lang="en">61 Long my eyes rove, upon the distance gazing.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-16a.4" xml:lang="en">I long but once to return; but when will that time be?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-16a.5" xml:lang="en">The birds fly home to their old haunts where they came from;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-16a.6" xml:lang="en">And the fox when he dies turns his head towards his earth.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-16a.7" xml:lang="en">That I was cast off and banished was truly for no crime.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-17a.1" xml:lang="en">By day and night I never can forget.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-18a.1" xml:lang="en">The Outpouring of sad thoughts</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-18a.2" xml:lang="en">1 My head is clouded over with melancholy thoughts.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-18a.3" xml:lang="en">Long and alone I sigh, but the pain grows only greater.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-18a.4" xml:lang="en">My thoughts are ravelled in a skein that cannot be disentangeled;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-18a.5" xml:lang="en">And when it comes to the night, the time drags endlessly.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-18a.6" xml:lang="en">5 Woe's me, how the autumn wind sets all the world a-scurrying!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-18a.7" xml:lang="en">See how from every point swirling and rushing it goes!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-18a.8" xml:lang="en">Often I think of my lord, so easily stirred to anger,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-18a.9" xml:lang="en">And it pains my heart with a grievous and bitter sorrow.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-18a.10" xml:lang="en">9 I would like to rise up and fly to him unbidden,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-18a.11" xml:lang="en">But seeing how others have fared, I restrain myself,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-18a.12" xml:lang="en">And instead I have set out my secret thoughts and put them into verse,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-18a.13" xml:lang="en">And offer them up to lay before the Fair One.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-18a.14" xml:lang="en">13 Once, my lord, you had made a tryst with me;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-18a.15" xml:lang="en">You said, 'The dusk shall be our meeting time.'</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-18a.16" xml:lang="en">But when you had gone half-way, you turned back again,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-18a.17" xml:lang="en">And instead of keeping tryst, you were of another mind.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-18a.18" xml:lang="en">17 You vaunted your comeliness before me;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-18a.19" xml:lang="en">You showed me all your fine array;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-18a.20" xml:lang="en">But the words you told me, you were not true to.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-18a.21" xml:lang="en">Why then should you went your anger on me?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-19a.2" xml:lang="en">21 I wanted to wait on this leisure and explain myself to him,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-19a.3" xml:lang="en">But my heart quaked fearfully and I did not dare.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-19a.4" xml:lang="en">Sad and troubled, I thought to go in to him;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-19a.5" xml:lang="en">But my heart was sore afflicted, and I held my peace for fear.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-19a.6" xml:lang="en">25 And when I unlocked these thoughts of mine and put them into words,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-19a.7" xml:lang="en">The Fragrant One feigned deafness and would not listen to them.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-19a.8" xml:lang="en">My words were direct, without fawning or flattery,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-19a.9" xml:lang="en">And so, sure enough, the courtier crowd found me a stumbling block.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-19a.10" xml:lang="en">29 That which I first set forth is there to see, plain and clear:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-19a.11" xml:lang="en">How can it be that today you suddenly cannot remember?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-19a.12" xml:lang="en">The words I offered you were a bitter medicine,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-19a.13" xml:lang="en">But only because I would have you shine with a brighter beauty.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-19a.14" xml:lang="en">33 I hoped that the Three and the Five would be your exemplars;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-19a.15" xml:lang="en">I pointed to Péng Xián as the pattern of what I would be.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-19a.16" xml:lang="en">There is no goal that cannot be attained by striving,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-19a.17" xml:lang="en">And, once attained, ours a fair fame that will not soon perish.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-19a.18" xml:lang="en">37 For goodness is not a thing to be got from outside us,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-19a.19" xml:lang="en">And fame not a thing we can fabricate from nothing.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-19a.20" xml:lang="en">Who without works has ever been rewarded?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-20a.1" xml:lang="en">Who without fruits ever reaped a harvest fair?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-20a.2" xml:lang="en">Shao Ge</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-20a.3" xml:lang="en">41 I unlocked my thoughts to set before the Fair One,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-20a.4" xml:lang="en">But neither night nor day would he show any discernment.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-20a.5" xml:lang="en">He vaunted his comeliness before me,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-20a.6" xml:lang="en">Disdained my words, and would not hear them.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-21a.2" xml:lang="en">Chang</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-21a.3" xml:lang="en">45 There is a bird from the South Country</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-21a.4" xml:lang="en">Come to settle north of the Hàn;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-21a.5" xml:lang="en">Most fair and rare and beautiful,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-21a.6" xml:lang="en">Forlorn he sits in this foreign land,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-21a.7" xml:lang="en">Alone and cut off from the rest of the flock,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-21a.8" xml:lang="en">With no one by to find him a mate.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-21a.9" xml:lang="en">55 The way is so far, that each day I remember less;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-21a.10" xml:lang="en">And I wish to make my plaint, but I cannot, for none will hear.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-21a.11" xml:lang="en">I gaze on the northern hills and my tears come falling,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-21a.12" xml:lang="en">Look down on the flowing waters and heave a dolorous sigh.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-21a.13" xml:lang="en">55 I long for the early summer to bring me shorter nights:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-21a.14" xml:lang="en">What dreary years the darkness now seems to me!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-21a.15" xml:lang="en">Though the road to Yǐng is a far, far distant journey,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-21a.16" xml:lang="en">Many a time each night my soul goes speeding there.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-21a.17" xml:lang="en">And because it does not know the twist and turns of the way there,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-21a.18" xml:lang="en">It takes the moon and stars as guides to lead it southwards,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-21a.19" xml:lang="en">Thinking to fly straight there; but still it can never reach it</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-21a.20" xml:lang="en">And flies distractedly, weaving this way and that.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-21a.21" xml:lang="en">63 Why should my soul be so true and constant?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-21a.22" xml:lang="en">The hearts of other men are not the same as my heart.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-21a.23" xml:lang="en">My advocate was weak and my matchmaker unable;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-21a.24" xml:lang="en">And so my lord still does not know the nature of my suit.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-22a.2" xml:lang="en">LUAN</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-22a.3" xml:lang="en">67 In the long shallows the current races, flowing to meet the deeps of the river;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-22a.4" xml:lang="en">There, with wild glances, I wander southwards, thinking to ease my heart a little.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-22a.5" xml:lang="en">But the sheer cliffs rising frowning and awful forbid my hopes of returning homewards.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-22a.6" xml:lang="en">Then, resolution with a rush returning, my steps unbidden lead me onwards.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-22a.7" xml:lang="en">Uncertain, faltering and fearful, I halt and take my lodgings at Běi-gū.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-22a.8" xml:lang="en">Sorrow and rage confuse my looks: I long to speed south with the flowing waters.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-22a.9" xml:lang="en">The sad sighs rack my soul; my spirit far is yearning.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-22a.10" xml:lang="en">Distant the road, obscure the place, and no one to rack my suit to!</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-22a.11" xml:lang="en">75 I tell thoughts in my song, thinking to ease my sorrow;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-22a.12" xml:lang="en">But my melancholy finds no course; to whom can these words be uttered?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-24a.1" xml:lang="en">Embracing Sand</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-24a.2" xml:lang="en">1 In the teeming late summer</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-24a.3" xml:lang="en">When flowers and trees burgeon,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-24a.4" xml:lang="en">My heart with endless sorrow laden,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-24a.5" xml:lang="en">Forth I went to the southern land.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-24a.6" xml:lang="en">5 Eyes strain unseeing into the hazy gloom</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-24a.7" xml:lang="en">Where a great quiet and stillness reign.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-24a.8" xml:lang="en">Disquieted and tormented,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-24a.9" xml:lang="en">I have met sorrow and long been afflicted.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-24a.10" xml:lang="en">9 I soothed my feelings, sought my purposes,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-24a.11" xml:lang="en">Bowed to my wrongs and still restrained myself.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-25a.2" xml:lang="en">Let others trim sqaure to fit the round:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-25a.3" xml:lang="en">I shall not cast the true measure away.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-25a.4" xml:lang="en">13 To change his first intent and alter his course</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-25a.5" xml:lang="en">Is a thing the noble man disdains.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-25a.6" xml:lang="en">I made my marking clear; I set my mind on the ink-line;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-25a.7" xml:lang="en">My former path I did not change.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-25a.8" xml:lang="en">17 Inwardly sound and of honest substance,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-25a.9" xml:lang="en">In this the great man exels so richly.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-25a.10" xml:lang="en">But when Chúi the cunning is not carving,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-25a.11" xml:lang="en">Who can tell how true a line he cuts?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-26a.2" xml:lang="en">21 When dark brocade is placed in the dark,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-26a.3" xml:lang="en">The dim-eyed will say it has no pattern.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-26a.4" xml:lang="en">And when Lí Lóu peers to discern the minutest things,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-26a.5" xml:lang="en">The purblind think that he must be sightless.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-26a.6" xml:lang="en">25 White is changed to black;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-26a.7" xml:lang="en">The high cast down and the low made high;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-26a.8" xml:lang="en">The phoenix languishes in a cage,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-26a.9" xml:lang="en">While hens and ducks can gambol free.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-26a.10" xml:lang="en">29 Jewels and stones are mixed together,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-26a.11" xml:lang="en">And in the same measure meted.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-26a.12" xml:lang="en">The courtier crowd are low and vulgar fellows;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-26a.13" xml:lang="en">They cannot understand the things I prize.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-26a.14" xml:lang="en">33 Great was the weight I carried, heavy the burdens I bore;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-26a.15" xml:lang="en">But I sank and stuck fast in the mire and could not get accross.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-26a.16" xml:lang="en">A jewel I wore in my bosom, a gem I clasped in my hand;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-26a.17" xml:lang="en">But, helpless, I knew no way whereby I could make them seen.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-26a.18" xml:lang="en">37 The dogs of the village bark in chorus;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-26a.19" xml:lang="en">They bark when they do not comprehend.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-26a.20" xml:lang="en">Genius they condemn and talent they suspect -</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-26a.21" xml:lang="en">Stupid and boorish that their manner is!</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-26a.22" xml:lang="en">41 Art and nature perfected lay within me hidden;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-26a.23" xml:lang="en">But the crowd did not know of the rare gifts that were mine.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-26a.24" xml:lang="en">Unused materials I had rich in store;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-26a.25" xml:lang="en">Yet no one knew the things that I posessed.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-27a.2" xml:lang="en">45 I multiplied kindness, redoubled righteousness;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-27a.3" xml:lang="en">Care and probity I had in plenty.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-27a.4" xml:lang="en">But it was not my lot to meet such as Chóng Huā;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-27a.5" xml:lang="en">So who could understand my behaviour?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-27a.6" xml:lang="en">49 It has always been so - this failure of happy meeting;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-27a.7" xml:lang="en">Though I do not know what can be the reason.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-27a.8" xml:lang="en">Tāng and Yǔ lived a great while ago -</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-27a.9" xml:lang="en">Too remote for me to long for!</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-27a.10" xml:lang="en">53 I must curb my rebelling pride and check my anger,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-27a.11" xml:lang="en">Restrain my heart, and force myself to bow.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-27a.12" xml:lang="en">I have met sorrow, but still will be unswerving;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-27a.13" xml:lang="en">I wish my resolution to be an example.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-27a.14" xml:lang="en">57 Along my road I will go, and in the north halt my journey.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-27a.15" xml:lang="en">But the day is dusky and turns towards the evening.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-27a.16" xml:lang="en">I will unlock my sorrow and ease my grief,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-27a.17" xml:lang="en">And end it all in the Great End.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-28a.2" xml:lang="en">LUAN</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-28a.3" xml:lang="en">61 The mighty waters of the Yuán and Xiāng with surging swell go rolling 113on their way;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-28a.4" xml:lang="en">The road is long, through places dark and drear, a way far and forlorn.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-28a.5" xml:lang="en">The nature I cherish in my bosom, the feelings I embrace, there are none to judge.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-28a.6" xml:lang="en">For when Bó Lè is dead and gone, how can the wonder-horse go coursing?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-28a.7" xml:lang="en">65 The lives of all men on earth have their ordained lot.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-28a.8" xml:lang="en">Let my heart be calm and my mind at ease: why should I be afraid?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-28a.9" xml:lang="en">Yet still, in mounting sorrow and anguish, I long lament and sigh.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-28a.10" xml:lang="en">For the world is muddy-witted; none can know me;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-28a.11" xml:lang="en">the heart of man cannot be told.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-28a.12" xml:lang="en">I know that death cannot be avoided,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-28a.13" xml:lang="en">therefore I will not grudge its coming.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-28a.14" xml:lang="en">70 To noble men I here plainly declare</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-28a.15" xml:lang="en">that I will be numbered with such as you.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-30a.1" xml:lang="en">Thinking of a Fair One</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-30a.2" xml:lang="en">1 Thinking of a Fair One,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-30a.3" xml:lang="en">I brush back my tears and long stand gazing.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-30a.4" xml:lang="en">Sundered from friends to plead for me, for the road is blocked,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-30a.5" xml:lang="en">I can frame no message to send to him,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-30a.6" xml:lang="en">And my burning wrongs, in tumult,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-30a.7" xml:lang="en">Are choked within and cannot find an outlet.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-30a.8" xml:lang="en">Until the dawn I pour out my inner heart;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-30a.9" xml:lang="en">But my will is thwarted and cannot reach its object.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-30a.10" xml:lang="en">9 I thought to trust my words to the floating clouds to carry,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-30a.11" xml:lang="en">But when I met Fēng Lóng, he would not take them.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-30a.12" xml:lang="en">I thought to send a message by the homing birds;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-30a.13" xml:lang="en">But they flew so fast and high that I could not reach them.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-30a.14" xml:lang="en">Blessed indeed was Gāo Xīn</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-30a.15" xml:lang="en">To meet the swallow that carried his gift for him.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-30a.16" xml:lang="en">If I could I would compromise and follow current fashion;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-30a.17" xml:lang="en">But I am ashamed to abase my mind and change from what I was.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-30a.18" xml:lang="en">17 I will pass through the years alone and encounter sorrows;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-30a.19" xml:lang="en">But my high-mettled heart will never change.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-30a.20" xml:lang="en">How can I tamely yield, and end my days in quietness?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-31a.1" xml:lang="en">How can I bring myself to change?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-31a.2" xml:lang="en">I know that my former roads hold no hope of advancement;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-31a.3" xml:lang="en">But I will not alter my course.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-31a.4" xml:lang="en">My chariot has overturned and my horses have fallen;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-31a.5" xml:lang="en">Yet still, alone, I cleave to this path, different from all the rest.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-31a.6" xml:lang="en">25 I harness the wonder horse, Qí Jì, and prepare to ride once more;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-31a.7" xml:lang="en">Cào(?) Fù holds the reins and drives for me;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-31a.8" xml:lang="en">But he falters and dawdles and will not gallop forward:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-31a.9" xml:lang="en">I shall stay a while and wait till the right time comes.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-31a.10" xml:lang="en">I point to the western folds of Bō-zhǒng:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-31a.11" xml:lang="en">The golden sunset shall be our thrysting time.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-32a.2" xml:lang="en">31 When springtime opens and brings forth the year,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-32a.3" xml:lang="en">And the bright sun tarries longer in the sky,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-32a.4" xml:lang="en">I shall unloose my heart's desire and yield to happiness,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-32a.5" xml:lang="en">And, following the River and the Xià, find solace for my sorrow.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-32a.6" xml:lang="en">35 I have culled wild parsley in the woodland thickets,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-32a.7" xml:lang="en">And gathered everlastings on the long island;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-32a.8" xml:lang="en">But alas! it was not my lot to be born in the olden time:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-32a.9" xml:lang="en">With whom can I enjoy these flowers that I have gathered?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-32a.10" xml:lang="en">39 I have plucked knotgrass and herbs of various hue,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-32a.11" xml:lang="en">And gathered all ready to twine a garland girdle.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-32a.12" xml:lang="en">A girdle I weave of rich and rare profusion;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-32a.13" xml:lang="en">But in the end it will fade and be rejected...</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-32a.14" xml:lang="en">43 I shall stay here a while and seek easement of my sadness</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-32a.15" xml:lang="en">By contemplating the South Men's strange behaviour.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-32a.16" xml:lang="en">When they are happy they conceal their gladness,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-32a.17" xml:lang="en">But are always quick in choler, always impatient...</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-33a.2" xml:lang="en">47 Sweet odours and rich savours mingle in wild abundance:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-33a.3" xml:lang="en">The flower and the fragrance come from within my breast;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-33a.4" xml:lang="en">Their ravishing sweetness reaches far and wide,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-33a.5" xml:lang="en">Suffusing my frame within and wafting outside me.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-33a.6" xml:lang="en">If my spirit and substance keep their integrity,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-33a.7" xml:lang="en">Though I dwell unseen and obscure, my fame can yet be bright.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-33a.8" xml:lang="en">53 I thought to make the dwarf fig plead my cause for me,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-33a.9" xml:lang="en">But I feared to climb up into his branches.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-33a.10" xml:lang="en">I thought to use the lotus as my matchmaker,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-33a.11" xml:lang="en">But I feared to lift my skirts up and wet my feet.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-33a.12" xml:lang="en">57 To climb up high I do not please;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-33a.13" xml:lang="en">To go down low I am not able.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-33a.14" xml:lang="en">Thus will my body never yield;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-33a.15" xml:lang="en">Thus do I halt in indecision.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-33a.16" xml:lang="en">61 I shall to the full pursue my former plan,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-33a.17" xml:lang="en">And never alter this course.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-33a.18" xml:lang="en">It is my lot to live in darkness...</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-33a.19" xml:lang="en">(The day is growing dark and) draws towards its close:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-33a.20" xml:lang="en">I must go while the bright sun has not yet reached his setting.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-33a.21" xml:lang="en">With my thoughts all on Péng Xián bending.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.1" xml:lang="en">Alas for the Days gone By</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.2" xml:lang="en">1 Alas for the days gone by! when I was trusted,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.3" xml:lang="en">And recieved the king's decrees to publish to the world;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.4" xml:lang="en">When I made our ancestors' acievements shine for posterity,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.5" xml:lang="en">And made plain whatever was doubtful in the laws.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.6" xml:lang="en">5 The land was rich and strong and its laws stood firm,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.7" xml:lang="en">And all was left to the Loyal Servant, while each day my lord took his ease.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.8" xml:lang="en">The secret affairs of state I carried locked in my heart.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.9" xml:lang="en">In those days, even if I was wrong, my lord did not correct me.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.10" xml:lang="en">But though my heart was pure and free from blemish,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.11" xml:lang="en">10 I met with slanderers who were jealous of me. [and I resent them???.]</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.12" xml:lang="en">My lord was full of anger towards his servant,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.13" xml:lang="en">Not waiting first to make sure wether the thing was so.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.14" xml:lang="en">For over my lord's wits these men had set a screen of darkness,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.15" xml:lang="en">Bemusing him with empty words and falsely deceiving him.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.16" xml:lang="en">15 And he, without examining to sound out the truth of it,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.17" xml:lang="en">Removed me to a far-off place and did not think of me,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.18" xml:lang="en">But trusted the filthy words of my traducers,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.19" xml:lang="en">Puffed up his anger and found fault in me.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.20" xml:lang="en">How innocent was I, his Loyal Sevant!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.21" xml:lang="en">20 Yet I was slandered and charges made against me.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.22" xml:lang="en">I was ashamed of the honest daylight,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.23" xml:lang="en">And hid myself in the dark to escape from it.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.24" xml:lang="en">I will stand above the Yuán or the Xiāng's dark waters,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.25" xml:lang="en">And steel myself to plunge in the flowing stream.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.26" xml:lang="en">25 I can bear to destroy my body and wipe out my name forever,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.27" xml:lang="en">But it grieves me that my lord is blinded and cannot see the light.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.28" xml:lang="en">Having no measure to judge men by,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.29" xml:lang="en">He causes the fragrant herb to hide in the marsh's tangle.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.30" xml:lang="en">How can I express my feelings and show my faithfulness?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.31" xml:lang="en">30 No, I will gladly die, and without repining.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.32" xml:lang="en">Since I am screened from my lord and thrust into obscurity,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-35a.33" xml:lang="en">I, his Loyal Servant, am left with no other way to turn.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.2" xml:lang="en">I have heard it said that Bó-lǐ Xi(?) was a prisoner;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.3" xml:lang="en">And Yī Yǐn cooked in a kitchen;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.4" xml:lang="en">35 Lǔ Wàng was a butcher at Zhao-ge;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.5" xml:lang="en">And Níng Qī sang as he fed his ox.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.6" xml:lang="en">If they had not met with their Tāng and Wǔ, their Huán and Mù,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.7" xml:lang="en">How would the world speak of them and know their names?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.8" xml:lang="en">Wú trusted the slanderer's tounge and did not ponder,</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.9" xml:lang="en">40 So Zǐ Xū died; but afterwards he was sorry.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.10" xml:lang="en">Jiè Zǐ-tui(?) was loyal; when he starved himself</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.11" xml:lang="en">Lord Wén remembered, and hastened after him.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.12" xml:lang="en">He made Mount Jiè a holy place and set bans about it</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.13" xml:lang="en">As retirement for his surpassing service.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.14" xml:lang="en">45 When he thought of their former close companionship,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.15" xml:lang="en">He put on white weeds and wept for him.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.16" xml:lang="en">Some men are honest and die martyrs;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.17" xml:lang="en">Some men are cheats and are never doubted.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.18" xml:lang="en">You would not look carefully and act upon the truth,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.19" xml:lang="en">50 But listened to the lies of slanderers.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.20" xml:lang="en">Now fragrant and foul are so mixed together,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.21" xml:lang="en">Who, though he laboured all night, could so discern between them?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.22" xml:lang="en">Why have the sweet flowers died so soon?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.23" xml:lang="en">A light frost descended and mowed them all down.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.24" xml:lang="en">55 You are so deaf to reason, so benighted,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.25" xml:lang="en">That slanderers and flatterers daily wax in your favour.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.26" xml:lang="en">From of old those envious of the good</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.27" xml:lang="en">Have called orchid and azalea unfit to wear at a girdle.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.28" xml:lang="en">Jealous of true beauty's fragrance,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.29" xml:lang="en">60 Mó Mǔ preens herself on her comeliness;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.30" xml:lang="en">But if you have Xī Shī's lovely face,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.31" xml:lang="en">The slanderer will get in and supplant you.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.32" xml:lang="en">I wished to set forth my thoughts and explain my actions:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.33" xml:lang="en">I little dreamed that this would be held a crime.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.34" xml:lang="en">65 That I was unjustly treated is clear as daylight,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.35" xml:lang="en">Plain as the stars above in their constellations.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.36" xml:lang="en">To harness swift steeds and go out coursing</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.37" xml:lang="en">And, without bit or rein, try to keep oneself in the chariot;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.38" xml:lang="en">Or on a raft to drift downstream with the current</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.39" xml:lang="en">70 And, without boat-sweep, try to keep afloat -</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.40" xml:lang="en">When you turn your back on all actions and let your sole heart rule,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.41" xml:lang="en">In comparison it is just like this.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.42" xml:lang="en">I would gladly die straight away and meet dissolution,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.43" xml:lang="en">If I did not fear that a greater ill might follow.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.44" xml:lang="en">75 With my words unsaid I could plunge into the waters,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-36a.45" xml:lang="en">But for thought of my blinded lord and his lack of understanding.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-38a.1" xml:lang="en">In Praise of the Orange-Tree</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-38a.2" xml:lang="en">1 Fairest of all God's trees, the orange came and settled here,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-38a.3" xml:lang="en">Commanded by him not to move, but only grow in the South Country.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-38a.4" xml:lang="en">Deep-rooted, firm and hard to shift: showing in this its singleness of purpose;</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-38a.5" xml:lang="en">Its leaves of green and pure white blossoms delight the eye of the beholder,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-38a.6" xml:lang="en">5 And the thick branches and spines so sharp, and the fine round fruits,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-38a.7" xml:lang="en">Green ones with yellow intermingling to make a pattern of gleaming brightness,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-38a.8" xml:lang="en">Pure white beneath the rich-hued surface: a parable of virtuous living;127</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-38a.9" xml:lang="en">Its lusty growth to the gardener's art respondent, producing beauty without blemish.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-39a.2" xml:lang="en">Oh, your young resolution has something different from the rest!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-39a.3" xml:lang="en">10 Alone and unmoving you stand: how can one not admire you?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-39a.4" xml:lang="en">Deep-rooted, hard to shift: truly you have no peer!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-39a.5" xml:lang="en">Alert to this world's ways you hold your ground, unyielding against the vulgar tide.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-39a.6" xml:lang="en">You have sealed your heart; you guard yourself with care; have never fallen 128into error;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-39a.7" xml:lang="en">Holding a nature free from bias, impartial even as Heaven and Earth are.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-39a.8" xml:lang="en">15 I would fade as you fade with the passing years and ever be your friend.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-39a.9" xml:lang="en">Pure and apart and free from sin, and strong in the order of your ways:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-39a.10" xml:lang="en">Though young in years, fit to be a teacher of men;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-39a.11" xml:lang="en">In your acts like Bó Yí: I set you up as my model.</seg>
</p>
<p>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-41a.1" xml:lang="en">1 Grieving at the eddying wind that shakes the orchid blossoms,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-41a.2" xml:lang="en">My heart is sorely troubled and within me sorrows;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-41a.3" xml:lang="en">For delicate things are by nature prone to fall;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-41a.4" xml:lang="en">And the faintest notes lead in the full orchestra.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-41a.5" xml:lang="en">How noble were the thoughts conceived by Péng Xián;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-41a.6" xml:lang="en">And his purpose so strong, and he ever mindful of it.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-41a.7" xml:lang="en">Though a man change his heart ten thousand times, how can he conceal it?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-41a.8" xml:lang="en">And who by decieving can succeed for long?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-41a.9" xml:lang="en">9 Birds and beasts cry out, calling to the flock.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-41a.10" xml:lang="en">When flowers crowd amidst dead halums, no fragrance comes from them.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-41a.11" xml:lang="en">Fish, by their thatch of scales are told apart;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-41a.12" xml:lang="en">But the dragon hides in the dark his patterned brightness.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-41a.13" xml:lang="en">Bitter and sweet herbs do not share the same field;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-41a.14" xml:lang="en">Orchid and sweet flag bloom unseen in solitary sweetness.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-41a.15" xml:lang="en">Only the good man's lasting beauty</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-41a.16" xml:lang="en">Preserves its aspect unchanged through succeeding ages.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-41a.17" xml:lang="en">17 Remote is the ideal that my thoughts aspire to:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-41a.18" xml:lang="en">I would be as the clouds that wander above in freedom.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-41a.19" xml:lang="en">But because there was that by which my high thoughts were shaken,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-41a.20" xml:lang="en">I have written these songs to make my meaning clear.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.2" xml:lang="en">21 The good man nurses his thoughts in isolation:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.3" xml:lang="en">So pollia and pepper I pluck for my lonely dwelling,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.4" xml:lang="en">And sigh upon choking sigh I heave</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.5" xml:lang="en">As I lie alone in my secret place and brood.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.6" xml:lang="en">25 The tears from my eyes and nose join in a sorry stream;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.7" xml:lang="en">Sleepless I lie with my thoughts until the dawn;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.8" xml:lang="en">All through the dreary wathces of the long night</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.9" xml:lang="en">I try to suppress my grief, but it will not go.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.10" xml:lang="en">Rising, I slowly wander forth,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.11" xml:lang="en">Thinking the exercise might bring some solace;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.12" xml:lang="en">But a heavy sigh breaks from my sorrowing breast,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.13" xml:lang="en">And gasping sobs rise, uncontrollable.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.14" xml:lang="en">33 I have twisted my longing thoughts to make a girdle;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.15" xml:lang="en">I have woven my bitter sorrow to make a stomach band.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.16" xml:lang="en">I broke a branch of the Ruò tree to shade me from the brightness;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.17" xml:lang="en">I would go wherever the wandering wind might blow me.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.18" xml:lang="en">The world grew misty; I could not see before me;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.19" xml:lang="en">My heart was leaping like boiling water.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.20" xml:lang="en">I clutched my belt and my coat-front to calm my spirits,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.21" xml:lang="en">And sorrowing I set out on my way.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.22" xml:lang="en">41 Swiftly the year is turning to decay,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.23" xml:lang="en">And my time draws gradually nearer.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.24" xml:lang="en">The marsh grasses dry up and break at the joints;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.25" xml:lang="en">The fragrance has faded; plants are thin and sparse.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.26" xml:lang="en">I rejoice that suffering has left my mind undaunted,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.27" xml:lang="en">Proving that the words I said were not idly spoken.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.28" xml:lang="en">But I would rather swiftly die and meet dissolution</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.29" xml:lang="en">Than have to endure this sorrow endlessly....</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.30" xml:lang="en">49 The orphan sobs and rubs his tears;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.31" xml:lang="en">The exile goes out and no more returns...</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.32" xml:lang="en">Who can reflect on this and not feel sad?...</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-42a.33" xml:lang="en">Glorifying the name of Péng Xián...</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-43a.2" xml:lang="en">53 I climbed a rock's summit and looked into the distance:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-43a.3" xml:lang="en">Far, far the road stretched, silent and deserted,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-43a.4" xml:lang="en">Entering places where no answering echo came,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-43a.5" xml:lang="en">Where the straining senses could perceive nothing.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-43a.6" xml:lang="en">57 Sorrow sits dark on me; all joy is gone;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-43a.7" xml:lang="en">My thoughts are filled with sadness that cannot be dispelled;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-43a.8" xml:lang="en">My heart is tied with bands of care that will not be unloosed;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-43a.9" xml:lang="en">My breath is twisted up and tied in a knot together.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-43a.10" xml:lang="en">61 Deep and dim in the distance, without a limit;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-43a.11" xml:lang="en">Vast, vacant verdancy, sans shape or form;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-43a.12" xml:lang="en">Even the faintest sound evokes an echo;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-43a.13" xml:lang="en">Even the simplest act becomes impossible.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-43a.14" xml:lang="en">Far on, far on, farther than can be measured;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-43a.15" xml:lang="en">Along, along, and all along never a bend.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-43a.16" xml:lang="en">In deepest melancholy of unassuaged grief;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-43a.17" xml:lang="en">Inconsolable, in sombrest gloom...</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-43a.18" xml:lang="en">69 Riding the great waves, drifting with the wind,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-43a.19" xml:lang="en">I could go to rest where Péng Xián dwells..</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-44a.2" xml:lang="en">71 I mounted a high cliff's rocky walls</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-44a.3" xml:lang="en">And stood at the woman rainbow's highest point;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-44a.4" xml:lang="en">Resting on the sky, speeding over the rainbow,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-44a.5" xml:lang="en">On I rushed until I touched the heavens.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-44a.6" xml:lang="en">I sipped cool drops of refreshing dew,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-44a.7" xml:lang="en">And rinsed my mouth with fine flakes of hoar frost.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-44a.8" xml:lang="en">I went in the Cave of the Winds to rest myself,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-44a.9" xml:lang="en">But woke up with a start, gasping for breath.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-44a.10" xml:lang="en">79 I lighted upon Kūn-lún. and peered into the mists;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-44a.11" xml:lang="en">I rested on Mín Mountain and looked down on the River.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-44a.12" xml:lang="en">I quailed as the leaping waters crashed among the boulders;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-44a.13" xml:lang="en">I listened to the shattering roar of the waves:</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-44a.14" xml:lang="en">ǐ Wild and tumultuous, without order,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-44a.15" xml:lang="en">Vast and immense, knowing no bounds;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-44a.16" xml:lang="en">Sometimes compressed and swollen without an outlet,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-44a.17" xml:lang="en">Sometimes racing uncurbed, with nothing to check them;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-44a.18" xml:lang="en">Undulating, now upwards and now downwards,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-44a.19" xml:lang="en">Swirling and swaying, now left and now right;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-44a.20" xml:lang="en">Flowing in currents, now forwards and now backwards,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-44a.21" xml:lang="en">Dividing ebb and flow into equal periods.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-44a.22" xml:lang="en">91 I watched the fiery vapours cloud on cloud ascending;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-44a.23" xml:lang="en">I saw them where they condense in the dewy vapour of mist;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-44a.24" xml:lang="en">I grieved when the frost and snow fell down together;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-44a.25" xml:lang="en">I listened to the booming shock of the tidal waters...</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-44a.26" xml:lang="en">95 I would borrow the daylight to travel back and forth,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-44a.27" xml:lang="en">Using a crooked switch of the yellow thorn for my horsewhip.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-44a.28" xml:lang="en">I sought out the places where Jiè Zǐ-tui(?) lived;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-44a.29" xml:lang="en">I saw the haunts where Bó Yí spent his exile.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-44a.30" xml:lang="en">My resolution was graven, I would not swerve from it;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-44a.31" xml:lang="en">My heart was attuned to the measure and would not leave it.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-45a.2" xml:lang="en">－</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-45a.3" xml:lang="en">101 I grieve for the high hopes of days gone by,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-45a.4" xml:lang="en">And sorrow for those that are yet to come.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-45a.5" xml:lang="en">I shall float down the river and the Huái until i enter the ocean,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-45a.6" xml:lang="en">And follow Zǐ Xū for my enjoyment.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-45a.7" xml:lang="en">I shall gaze on the Yellow River's islands,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-45a.8" xml:lang="en">And mourn at the place of Shēn Tu'2s noble end:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-45a.9" xml:lang="en">Repeatedly he rebuked his lord, but his lord would not listen:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_004-45a.10" xml:lang="en">But what good did it do to clasp a great stone and drown?...</seg>
</p>
<p>
</p>
</div>
<div><head>5 遠遊	Far-off Journey</head>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-2a.2" xml:lang="en">9 I thought of the limitless vastness of the universe,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-2a.3" xml:lang="en">I wept for the long affliction of man's life.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-2a.4" xml:lang="en">Those that had gone before I should never see;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-2a.5" xml:lang="en">And those yet to come I should never know of.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-2a.6" xml:lang="en">13 Restless I paced, with my mind on distant things;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-2a.7" xml:lang="en">Despairing, frustrated, consumed with constant yearning.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-2a.8" xml:lang="en">My thoughts were wild and wandered distractedly;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-2a.9" xml:lang="en">My heart was melancholy and consumed with sadness.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-2a.10" xml:lang="en">17 My spirit darted forth and did not return to me,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-2a.11" xml:lang="en">And my body, left tenantless, grew withered and lifeless.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-2a.12" xml:lang="en">Then I looked into myself to strengthen my resulution,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-2a.13" xml:lang="en">And sought to learn from where the primal spirit issues.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-2a.14" xml:lang="en">21 In emptiness and silence I found serenity,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-2a.15" xml:lang="en">In tranquil inaction I gained true satisfaction.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-3a.2" xml:lang="en">I heard how once Red Pine had washed the world's dust off:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-3a.3" xml:lang="en">I would model myself on the pattern he had left me.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-3a.4" xml:lang="en">25. I honoured the wondrous powers of the Pure Ones;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-3a.5" xml:lang="en">And those of past ages who had become Immortals.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-3a.6" xml:lang="en">They departed in the flux of change and vanished from men's sight,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-3a.7" xml:lang="en">Leaving a famous name that endures after them.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-3a.8" xml:lang="en">29 I marvelled how Fù Yuè lived on in a star;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-3a.9" xml:lang="en">I admired Hán Zhòng for attaining Oneness.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-3a.10" xml:lang="en">Their bodies grew dim and faded into the distance;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-3a.11" xml:lang="en">They left the crowded world behind and withdrew themselves.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-3a.12" xml:lang="en">33 In the ether's transformations they rose upwards,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-3a.13" xml:lang="en">With godlike swiftness miraculously moving. (C: so the spirits marvel)</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-3a.14" xml:lang="en">Sometimes men see them, in remote, uncertain glimpses,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-3a.15" xml:lang="en">As their bright spirit forms dart across the sky.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-3a.16" xml:lang="en">37 Leaving the dust behind, they shed their impurities,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-3a.17" xml:lang="en">Never to return again to their old homes.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-3a.18" xml:lang="en">Escaping all life's troubles they had no more need to fear them,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-3a.19" xml:lang="en">But no one in the world knows where they went to.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-4a.2" xml:lang="en">41 I came to be fearful of the passing of the seasons,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-4a.3" xml:lang="en">Of the Bright God's relentless journey to the west.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-4a.4" xml:lang="en">It grieved me to think that when the fine frost descended,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-4a.5" xml:lang="en">All my fragrant flowers would prematurely fade.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-4a.6" xml:lang="en">I wanted some time to roam in leisurely enjoyment,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-4a.7" xml:lang="en">I had gone through the length of years with nothing yet achieved.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-4a.8" xml:lang="en">47 With whom could I enjoy the fragrance that was left me?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-4a.9" xml:lang="en">Long I stood against the wind, unburdening my heart.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-4a.10" xml:lang="en">Gāo Yáng lived far from me in a distant time:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-4a.11" xml:lang="en">How could I ...?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-5a.2" xml:lang="en">-</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-5a.3" xml:lang="en">51. Spring and autumn hurried by, never delaying,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-5a.4" xml:lang="en">I could not go on staying in my old home for ever.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-5a.5" xml:lang="en">Xuān Yuán was too remote for me to aspire to;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-5a.6" xml:lang="en">I will follow Wáng Qiáo for my delight.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-5a.7" xml:lang="en">55 I supped the Six Essences; drank the Night Dew (hàngxiè)</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-5a.8" xml:lang="en">Rinsed my mouth in the Sun Mist; savoured the Morning Brightness.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-5a.9" xml:lang="en">Conserving the pure elements of the divine;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-5a.10" xml:lang="en">Absorbing the subtle essence and rejecting the grosser parts.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-5a.11" xml:lang="en">59 Drifting in the wake of the gentle south wind,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-5a.12" xml:lang="en">I travelled to Nán-cháo in a single journey.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-5a.13" xml:lang="en">There I saw Master Wáng and made him salutation,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-5a.14" xml:lang="en">And asked him about the balance made by unifying essence.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-6a.2" xml:lang="en">63 He said:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-6a.3" xml:lang="en">"The Way can only be received,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-6a.4" xml:lang="en">it cannot be given.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-6a.5" xml:lang="en">Small, it has no content;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-6a.6" xml:lang="en">great, it has no bounds.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-6a.7" xml:lang="en">Keep your soul from confusion,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-6a.8" xml:lang="en">and it will come naturally; [become all natural]</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-6a.9" xml:lang="en">By unifying essence; strenghten the spirit;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-6a.10" xml:lang="en">preserve it inside you in the midnight hour.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-6a.11" xml:lang="en">Await it in emptiness,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-6a.12" xml:lang="en">before even Inaction.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-6a.13" xml:lang="en">All other things proceed from this:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-6a.14" xml:lang="en">this is the Door of Power."</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-7a.2" xml:lang="en">69 Having heard this precious teaching, I departed,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-7a.3" xml:lang="en">And swiftly prepared to start off on my journey.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-7a.4" xml:lang="en">I met the Feathered Men on the Hill of Cinnabar;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-7a.5" xml:lang="en">I tarried in the ancient land of Immortality.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-7a.6" xml:lang="en">73 In the morning I washed my hair in the Gulf of Brightness,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-7a.7" xml:lang="en">In the evening I dried myself on the coasts of heaven.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-7a.8" xml:lang="en">I sipped the subtle liquor of the Flying Spring,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-7a.9" xml:lang="en">And held in my bosom the flower-bright wǎn-yǎn jewel.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-7a.10" xml:lang="en">77 My jade-like countenance flushed with radiant colour [pīngyǐwànyán];</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-7a.11" xml:lang="en">Purified, my vital essence started to grow stronger;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-7a.12" xml:lang="en">My corporeal parts dissolved to a soft suppleness[zhuó]</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-7a.13" xml:lang="en">And my spirit grew lissom [miǎo] and eager for movement.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-7a.14" xml:lang="en">ī How fine was fiery nature of the south land!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-7a.15" xml:lang="en">How lovely the winter blooming of the cassia!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-7a.16" xml:lang="en">But the mountain was forlorn with no beasts upon it;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-7a.17" xml:lang="en">The moor was a lonely place with no man there.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-7a.18" xml:lang="en">I restrained my restless spirit and mounted the empyrean;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-7a.19" xml:lang="en">I clung to a floating cloud to ride aloft on.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-7a.20" xml:lang="en">87 I bade heaven's porter open up his barrier,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-7a.21" xml:lang="en">And stand by his gate awaiting my arrival.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-7a.22" xml:lang="en">I summoned Fēng Lóng; I made him ride ahead</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-7a.23" xml:lang="en">And ask the way to the Palace of Mystery.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-7a.24" xml:lang="en">91 Passing through the Bright Walls I entered the House of God.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-7a.25" xml:lang="en">Visited the Week Star and gazed on the Pure City.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.2" xml:lang="en">In the morning I set off from the Court of Heaven;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.3" xml:lang="en">In the evening Wēi Lǘ came in sight below.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.4" xml:lang="en">95 I marshalled in order my ten thousand chariots:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.5" xml:lang="en">And moved slowly forwards in splendid prosession.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.6" xml:lang="en">Eight dragons drew my car, coiling and curvetting,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.7" xml:lang="en">Over it a cloud-banner flapped upon the wind.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.8" xml:lang="en">99 The standards we carried bore rainbow devices:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.9" xml:lang="en">Five contrasting colours, dazzling to behold.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.10" xml:lang="en">Splendidly the yoke-horses bowed and tossed their heads;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.11" xml:lang="en">Proudly the trace-horses arched and curved themselves.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.12" xml:lang="en">103 A din and bustle rose up confusedly,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.13" xml:lang="en">As our colourful, many-assorted train began to move.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.14" xml:lang="en">I grasped the reins and, with my whip, I signalled the direction:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.15" xml:lang="en">The first part of our journey should be to visit Gōu Máng.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.16" xml:lang="en">107 We crossed the eastern heaven, wheeling to the right hand.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.17" xml:lang="en">I sent Fēi Lián on ahead to clear the way for us.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.18" xml:lang="en">The sky was just beginning to flush before the sunrise</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.19" xml:lang="en">As we forded the waters of the Pool of Heaven.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.20" xml:lang="en">111 The Wind God meanwhile was riding on ahead,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.21" xml:lang="en">Clearing the dust away to make it clean and cool.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.22" xml:lang="en">Phoenixes sweeping overhead bore up my pennant,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.23" xml:lang="en">Then we met Rù Shōu in the western heaven.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.24" xml:lang="en">115 I took hold of the Broom Star to use it as a banner;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.25" xml:lang="en">I brandished the Dipper's Handle as my baton.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.26" xml:lang="en">Up and down our long train went, plunging and soaring,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.27" xml:lang="en">Drifting on the moving waves of the fleeting mist.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.28" xml:lang="en">119 The daylight was fading and darkness was gathering</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.29" xml:lang="en">As I summoned Xuán Wǔ to serve in my train.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.30" xml:lang="en">I made Wén Chāng follow, too, to marshal the procession,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.31" xml:lang="en">Disposing the gods in their places in my retinue.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.32" xml:lang="en">123 Far the road stretched ahead, endlessly onward,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.33" xml:lang="en">We slowed down the pace as we crossed the height of heaven.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.34" xml:lang="en">The Rain God went on my left hand to guide me;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.35" xml:lang="en">The Thunder God went on my right hand as bodyguard.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.36" xml:lang="en">127 I wanted to leave for good, to forget about returning:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.37" xml:lang="en">My mind was exhalted with a reckless sense of freedom;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.38" xml:lang="en">A boundless satisfaction suffused my inner being:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.39" xml:lang="en">I wanted to yield to this voluptuous contentment.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.40" xml:lang="en">131 Traversing the blue sky, I was wandering freely,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.41" xml:lang="en">When suddenly I glimpsed my old home below me.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.42" xml:lang="en">My groom was homesick and my own heart downcast;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.43" xml:lang="en">The trace-horses looked back and would not go forward.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.44" xml:lang="en">135 I pictured my dear ones in imagination,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.45" xml:lang="en">And, with a heavy sigh, I brushed the tears away.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.46" xml:lang="en">Then slowly I drifted on, rising even higher,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.47" xml:lang="en">Supressing these wilful thoughts, in control once more.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.48" xml:lang="en">139 Pointing to the Fiery God, I made a straight line towards him:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-8a.49" xml:lang="en">I wished to journey onwards to the world's southern shore.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-9a.2" xml:lang="en">I gazed into the emptiness there, beyond the world's end;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-9a.3" xml:lang="en">Then onwards still I floated, over that watery vastness.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-9a.4" xml:lang="en">143 But Zhù Róng stood in my way, warning me to turn back.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-9a.5" xml:lang="en">And I bade the Sea God dance with the River God.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-9a.6" xml:lang="en">147 They played the 'Pool of Heaven', then struck up 'To the Clouds',</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-9a.7" xml:lang="en">Then the two goddesses performed the Nine Sháo Songs.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-9a.10" xml:lang="en">They lined water monsters up to join them in the dance:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-9a.11" xml:lang="en">How their bodies coiled and writhed in undulating motion!</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-9a.12" xml:lang="en">151 Gracefully the woman-rainbow made circles round them;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-9a.13" xml:lang="en">Phoenixes soarded up and hovered overhead.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-9a.14" xml:lang="en">The music swelled and swelled into infinity.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-9a.15" xml:lang="en">After that I left them and resumed my wandering.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-9a.16" xml:lang="en">155 All keeping close in step, on and on we galloped,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-9a.17" xml:lang="en">Till, at the world's other end, we came to the Gate of Coldness.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-9a.18" xml:lang="en">There I raced the rushing wind to the Freezing Fountain;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-9a.19" xml:lang="en">I followed Zhuān Xū over the piled-up ice.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-9a.20" xml:lang="en">159 I turned from my path to cross the realm of Xuān Míng;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-9a.21" xml:lang="en">Bestriding the Dividers, I looked back behind me.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-9a.22" xml:lang="en">I summoned Qián Léi to appear before me</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-9a.23" xml:lang="en">And caused him to go in front in the level way.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-9a.24" xml:lang="en">163 I toured the Four Outlands,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-9a.25" xml:lang="en">Traversed the Six Regions,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-9a.26" xml:lang="en">Up to the lightning's fissure,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-9a.27" xml:lang="en">And down to the Great Abyss.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-9a.28" xml:lang="en">167 In the sheer depths below, the earth was invisible;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-9a.29" xml:lang="en">In the vastness above, the sky could not be seen.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-9a.30" xml:lang="en">When I looked, my startled eyes saw nothing;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-9a.31" xml:lang="en">When I listened, no sound met my amazed ear.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-9a.32" xml:lang="en">Transcending Inaction, I came to Purity,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_005-9a.33" xml:lang="en">And entered the neighbourhood of the Great Beginning.</seg>
</p>
<p>
</p>
</div>
<div><head>6 卜居	Divination</head>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.8" xml:lang="en">And so he called on the Great Diviner, Zhān Yǐn of Zhèng, and said:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.9" xml:lang="en">`I have an uncertainty in my mind</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.10" xml:lang="en">which I would like you to resolve for me.'</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.11" xml:lang="en">Zhān Yǐn accordingly set out his divining-stalks and dusted his turtle-shell.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.12" xml:lang="en">'My lord,'he said, 'what are your instructions?'</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.13" xml:lang="en">－</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.14" xml:lang="en">'Is it better,' Qū Yuán asked him, to be painstakingly honest,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.15" xml:lang="en">simple-hearted and loyal,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.16" xml:lang="en">or to keep out of trouble by welcoming each change as it comes?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.21" xml:lang="en">`Is it better to risk one's life</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.22" xml:lang="en">by speaking truthfully and without concealment,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.23" xml:lang="en">or to save one's skin by following the whims</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.24" xml:lang="en">of the wealhty and highly placed?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.25" xml:lang="en">'Is it better to preserve one's integrity</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.26" xml:lang="en">by means of a lofty detatchment,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.27" xml:lang="en">or to wait on a king's mistress with</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.28" xml:lang="en">flattery, fawning,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.29" xml:lang="en">and strained, smirking laughter?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.30" xml:lang="en">Is it better to be honest and incorruptible</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.31" xml:lang="en">and to keep oneself pure,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.32" xml:lang="en">or to be accomodating and slippery,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.33" xml:lang="en">to be compliant</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.34" xml:lang="en">as lard or leater?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.35" xml:lang="en">'Is it better to have the aspiring spirit of a thousand li 3 stallion,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.36" xml:lang="en">or to drift this way and that like a duck on water,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.37" xml:lang="en">saving oneself</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.38" xml:lang="en">by rising and falling with the waves?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.39" xml:lang="en">'Is it better to run neck and neck with the swiftest,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.40" xml:lang="en">or to follow in the footsteps of a broken hack?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.41" xml:lang="en">'Is it better to match wing-tips with the flying swan,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.42" xml:lang="en">or to dispute for scraps with chicken and ducks?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.43" xml:lang="en">'Of these alterenatives, which is auspicious and which is ill-omened?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.44" xml:lang="en">Which is to be avoided and which to be followed?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.45" xml:lang="en">The world is turbulent and impure;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.46" xml:lang="en">They call a cicada's wing heavy</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.47" xml:lang="en">and a ton weight light;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.48" xml:lang="en">The brazen bell is smashed and discarded;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.49" xml:lang="en">the earthen crock is thunderously sounded;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.50" xml:lang="en">The slanderer struts proudly,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.51" xml:lang="en">the wise man lurks unknown.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.52" xml:lang="en">Alas, I am silenced:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.53" xml:lang="en">who can know of my integrity?'</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.54" xml:lang="en">Zhān Yǐn threw aside the divining stalks and excused himself.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.55" xml:lang="en">'There are times,' he said, 'when a foot is too short;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.56" xml:lang="en">and there are times when an inch is too long.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.57" xml:lang="en">There are cases in which the instruments are of no avail,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.58" xml:lang="en">in which knowledge can give no enlightenment.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.59" xml:lang="en">There are things to which my calculations cannot attain,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.60" xml:lang="en">over which the divinity has no power.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.61" xml:lang="en">My lord, for one with your mind</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.62" xml:lang="en">and with resolution such as yours</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_006-1a.63" xml:lang="en">the turtle and the divining stalks are really unable to be of help.'</seg>
</p>
<p>
</p>
</div>
<div><head>7 漁父	The Fisherman</head>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-1a.7" xml:lang="en">A fisherman caught sight of him.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-1a.8" xml:lang="en">'Are you the Lord of the Three Wards?' said the fisherman.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-1a.9" xml:lang="en">'What has brought you to his pass?'</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-1a.10" xml:lang="en">'Because all the world is muddy and I alone am clear,'</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-1a.11" xml:lang="en">said Qū Yuán,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-1a.12" xml:lang="en">`and because all men are drunken and I alone am sober,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-1a.13" xml:lang="en">I have been sent into exile.'</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-1a.14" xml:lang="en">'The Wise Man is not chained to material circumstances,'</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-1a.15" xml:lang="en">said the fisherman,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-1a.16" xml:lang="en">'but can move as the world moves.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-1a.17" xml:lang="en">If all the world is muddy,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-1a.18" xml:lang="en">why not help them to stir up the mud and beat up the waves?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-1a.19" xml:lang="en">And if all men are drunk,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-1a.20" xml:lang="en">why not sup their dregs and swill their lees?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-1a.21" xml:lang="en">Why get yourself exiled</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-1a.22" xml:lang="en">because of your deep thoughts and your fine aspirations?'</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-1a.23" xml:lang="en">Qū Yuán replied,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-1a.24" xml:lang="en">'I have heard it said:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-1a.25" xml:lang="en">"He who has just washed his hair should brush his hat;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-1a.26" xml:lang="en">and he who has just bathed should shake his clothes."</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-1a.27" xml:lang="en">How can I submit my spotless purity</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-1a.28" xml:lang="en">to the dirt of others?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-1a.29" xml:lang="en">I would rather cast myself into the waters of the river</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-1a.30" xml:lang="en">and be buried in the bowels of fishes,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-1a.31" xml:lang="en">than hide my shining light</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-1a.32" xml:lang="en">in the dark and dust of the world.'</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-1a.33" xml:lang="en">The fisherman, with a faint smile,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-1a.34" xml:lang="en">struck his paddle in the water and made off.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-2a.2" xml:lang="en">And as he went he sang:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-2a.3" xml:lang="en">'When the Cāng-làng's waters are clear,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-2a.4" xml:lang="en">I can wash my hat-strings in them;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-2a.5" xml:lang="en">When the Cāng-làng's waters are muddy,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-2a.6" xml:lang="en">I can wash my feet in them.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_007-2a.7" xml:lang="en">With that he was gone, and did not speak again.</seg>
</p>
<p>
</p>
</div>
<div><head>8 九辯	Nine Changes</head>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-1a.12" xml:lang="en">5 Still and deep:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-1a.13" xml:lang="en">the streams have drunk full and the waters are clear.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-1a.14" xml:lang="en">Heartsick and sighing sore:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-1a.15" xml:lang="en">for the cold draws on and strikes into a man;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-1a.16" xml:lang="en">Distraught and disappointed:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-1a.17" xml:lang="en">leaving the old and to new places turning;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-1a.18" xml:lang="en">Afflicted:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-1a.19" xml:lang="en">the poor esquire has lost his office and his heart rebels;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-1a.20" xml:lang="en">Desolate:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-1a.21" xml:lang="en">on his long journey he rests with never a friend;</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-1a.22" xml:lang="en">10 Melancholy:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-1a.23" xml:lang="en">he nurses a private sorrow.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-1a.24" xml:lang="en">The flutering swallows leave on their homeward journey;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-1a.25" xml:lang="en">The forlorn cicada makes no sound;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-1a.26" xml:lang="en">The wild geese call as they travel southwards;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-1a.27" xml:lang="en">The partridge chatters with a mournful cry.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-1a.28" xml:lang="en">15 Alone he waits for the dawn to come, unsleeping,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-1a.29" xml:lang="en">Mourning with the cricket, the midnight traveller.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-1a.30" xml:lang="en">His time draws on apace: already half is gone;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-2a.1" xml:lang="en">Yet still he languishes, nothing accomplished.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-2a.2" xml:lang="en">1 Sad and in sore straits I dwell alone.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-2a.3" xml:lang="en">There is a Fair One, from my heart never sundered.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-2a.4" xml:lang="en">I have left home and country, and gone a traveller to distant places.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-2a.5" xml:lang="en">Far have I wandered: where will my journeying end?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-2a.7" xml:lang="en">5 But my lord would have none of it. What could I do?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-2a.8" xml:lang="en">Storing my resentment up, husbanding my anguish,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-2a.9" xml:lang="en">I was so sick at heart that I forgot to eat.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-2a.10" xml:lang="en">I longed but once to see him and give my thoughts expression,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-2a.11" xml:lang="en">But the heart of my lord was not the same as mine;</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-2a.12" xml:lang="en">10 And though my chariot was harnessed, I had to turn back again:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-2a.13" xml:lang="en">It grieved me bitterly that I could not see him.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-2a.14" xml:lang="en">I learned upon the chariot-board and heaved a heavy sigh,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-2a.15" xml:lang="en">And in a stream the tears ran down and wet the chariot-rail.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-2a.16" xml:lang="en">My high aspirations are cut off without hope;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-2a.17" xml:lang="en">15 I have fallen on dark, troubled times; I am lost and bevildered;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-2a.18" xml:lang="en">But though my private sorrow may be never-ending,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-2a.19" xml:lang="en">The heart that beats in me will always be loyal and true.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.2" xml:lang="en">1 High Heaven divides the four seasons equally,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.3" xml:lang="en">But I am grieved only by the chilly autumn.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.4" xml:lang="en">The white dew has fallen on the hundred flowers;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.5" xml:lang="en">The tóng and catalpa trees will soon grow thin and bare.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.6" xml:lang="en">5 Gone now is the radiance of the bright sun,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.7" xml:lang="en">And come the dreary watches of the longer nights.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.8" xml:lang="en">I have left behind my blossom-burgeoning prime:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.9" xml:lang="en">Sore and withered, I am full of melancholy.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.10" xml:lang="en">First autumn heralds with warning of white dew;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.11" xml:lang="en">10 Then winter redoubles rigour with bitter frost.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.12" xml:lang="en">High summer's fecund forces are gathered up,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.13" xml:lang="en">Then trapped and buried away in winter's prison.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.14" xml:lang="en">Leaves are sickly and lacking colour;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.15" xml:lang="en">Stems are criss-crossed in confusion,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.16" xml:lang="en">15 The boughs are thin and withered-looking;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.17" xml:lang="en">The tapering twigs are sad to see.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.18" xml:lang="en">Things creep in hue towards their coming end,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.19" xml:lang="en">Their whole appearance wasted away and sick.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.20" xml:lang="en">I think of the rich profusion soon to fall,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.21" xml:lang="en">20 And grieve that I missed the time when I might have met my master.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.22" xml:lang="en">Seizing the reins, I slowed down the pace of my horses,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.23" xml:lang="en">Thinking to find some pleasure in idle wandering;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.24" xml:lang="en">But my years move swiftly by and will soon be ended:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.25" xml:lang="en">I fear that a good old age will not be for me.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.26" xml:lang="en">25 I mourn that I was not born in a better time,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.27" xml:lang="en">And have fallen on this mad and fearful age.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.28" xml:lang="en">Slowly I pace or solitary stand,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.29" xml:lang="en">While the cricket chirps here in the west hall.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.30" xml:lang="en">My heart is afraid and sorely shaken;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.31" xml:lang="en">30 I have so many sources of sorrow.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.32" xml:lang="en">I look up to the bright moon and sigh,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-3a.33" xml:lang="en">And walk underneath the stars until daylight comes.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-4a.2" xml:lang="en">1 I grieve for the orchid blossoms thickly spreading</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-4a.3" xml:lang="en">That grow so gaily in the great courtyard.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-4a.4" xml:lang="en">Alas that these flowers should be without any fruits, [How come?]</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-4a.5" xml:lang="en">And, fluttering, bow to every wind and shower!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-4a.6" xml:lang="en">5 I had thought that my lord would only wear these orchids,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-4a.7" xml:lang="en">But he treated them no differently from any other flower.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-4a.8" xml:lang="en">I was sad that my matchless thoughts could find no way to him,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-4a.9" xml:lang="en">And resolved to leave my lord and fly off high.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-4a.10" xml:lang="en">My heart was grieved and sorely pained within me;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-4a.11" xml:lang="en">10 I longed but once to see him, so that all might be made clear.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-4a.12" xml:lang="en">How hard to be estranged when I had not offended!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-4a.13" xml:lang="en">My bosom was tormented with bitter anguish.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-4a.14" xml:lang="en">How should I not think anxiously of my lord?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-4a.15" xml:lang="en">But nine gates, gate within gate, divide me from him.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-4a.16" xml:lang="en">15 Fierce, snarling dogs run out from them and bark,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-4a.17" xml:lang="en">And they bar the way to him and will not let me through.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-4a.18" xml:lang="en">High Heaven overflows; the autumn rains are with us,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-4a.19" xml:lang="en">And it seems that Earth will never be dry again.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-4a.20" xml:lang="en">I, only I, am deprived of nurturing moisture,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-4a.21" xml:lang="en">20 And look up at the floating clouds with a heavy sigh.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.2" xml:lang="en">1 What wonderful craftsmen, this modern generation!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.3" xml:lang="en">They abandon the inked string, preferring their own guidelines;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.4" xml:lang="en">Fine steeds they reject when they would go out driving;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.5" xml:lang="en">They prefer to take the road whipping a broken nag.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.6" xml:lang="en">5 It is not that in this age there are no fine steeds;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.7" xml:lang="en">Simply that there is no one skillful enough to drive them.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.8" xml:lang="en">The fine steed sees that the man at the rein is a tyro,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.9" xml:lang="en">So he kicks up his heels and takes himself far off.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.10" xml:lang="en">Wild geese and ducks gobble millet and water-weed,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.11" xml:lang="en">10 But the phoenix soars high up into the sky.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.12" xml:lang="en">(If you take a square handle to use on a round chisel,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.13" xml:lang="en">I am certain it will not fit and you will not make it go in.)</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.14" xml:lang="en">The common birds all have their perches to go to;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.15" xml:lang="en">The phoenix hovers distractedly, having no place.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.16" xml:lang="en">15 I would willingly gag my mouth and say nothing,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.17" xml:lang="en">Had I not once enjoyed rich favours from my lord.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.18" xml:lang="en">Duke Tài was ninety years old before he was honored,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.19" xml:lang="en">Simply because, before that, he had never met his match.)</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.20" xml:lang="en">What of the fine steed? Where is he to turn?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.21" xml:lang="en">20 What of the phoenix? Where is he to rest?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.22" xml:lang="en">The old ways are altered, customs changed, the world decays:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.23" xml:lang="en">The fancier of today extols a fine fat look.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.24" xml:lang="en">The good steed lies hidden and will not show himself;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.25" xml:lang="en">The phoenix flies high and will not come down and alight.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.26" xml:lang="en">25 If even birds and beasts know how to maintain their virtue,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.27" xml:lang="en">It need not be asked why the good man does not stay.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.28" xml:lang="en">The steed, no longer coursing, is searching for a driver;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.29" xml:lang="en">The phoenix has no apetite and forgets to eat.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.30" xml:lang="en">My lord has banished me far off and will not examnine my cause:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.31" xml:lang="en">30 Even though I wish to be loyal, I have no means to show it.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.32" xml:lang="en">I should like to keep silent and sunder all links with him;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.33" xml:lang="en">But I dare not forget the great kindness he once showed me.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.34" xml:lang="en">Alone with my grief, I suffer the more deeply;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.35" xml:lang="en">And my choking anger knows no appeasement.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.36" xml:lang="en">1 Dew falls and the bitter frost follows to afflict me,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.37" xml:lang="en">And my heart is distraught and will not be comforted.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.38" xml:lang="en">Sleet and snow, thickly commingling, harder and harder come down,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.39" xml:lang="en">And I know that the time is near when I must meet my end.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.40" xml:lang="en">5 I wish that by some lucky chance I might be forgiven;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.41" xml:lang="en">But I shall soon die, along with the moorland grasses.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.42" xml:lang="en">I wish I could set off unbidden and fly straight to him,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.43" xml:lang="en">But the road to him is blocked and impassable.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.44" xml:lang="en">I wish I could follow the other's route and ride the easy way,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.45" xml:lang="en">10 But that, too, is no good: I do not know how to do it.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.46" xml:lang="en">And so I stop midway in perplexity,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.47" xml:lang="en">Grieving and hesistant; unable to turn back.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.48" xml:lang="en">And though dull and stupid by nature and poor in talents,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-5a.49" xml:lang="en">Truly I am not skilled to imitate their fashion.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-6a.2" xml:lang="en">1 I love the great spirit of Shēn Bāo-xū,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-6a.3" xml:lang="en">But I fear this present age's unsteadfastness.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-6a.4" xml:lang="en">What wonderful craftsmen, this modern generation!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-6a.5" xml:lang="en">They efface the marked lines and carve after their own fancy.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-6a.6" xml:lang="en">5 I alone am staunch and will not follow them,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-6a.7" xml:lang="en">Wishing to take as my guidelines the pattern thought by the Sages.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-6a.8" xml:lang="en">To live in an impure world and be honored</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-6a.9" xml:lang="en">Is not a thing my heart delights in:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-6a.10" xml:lang="en">Rather than by unrighteous means be famous,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-6a.11" xml:lang="en">10 I would live poor and keep myslef above them.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-6a.12" xml:lang="en">I can eat without greed and yet be full;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-6a.13" xml:lang="en">Dress without luxury and still be warm.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-6a.14" xml:lang="en">I love the spirit of that old poet:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-6a.15" xml:lang="en">I should take as my motto what he said of the 'bread of idleness'.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-6a.16" xml:lang="en">15 Full of impatient thoughts, with no end or beginning,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-6a.17" xml:lang="en">In this vast wilderness that has no limit -</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-6a.18" xml:lang="en">I have no clothes and furs to protect me from the winter's cold,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-6a.19" xml:lang="en">And I fear I shall shortly die and not live to see the warm spring.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-7a.2" xml:lang="en">1 When I think of the long nights of late autumn,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-7a.3" xml:lang="en">My heart is tormented and full of grief.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-7a.4" xml:lang="en">My springs and autumns are growing in number;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-7a.5" xml:lang="en">Sadly I lament my lot.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-7a.6" xml:lang="en">5 The seasons come and go, making up the year;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-7a.7" xml:lang="en">Light and dark alternate: I scarce can keep abreast.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-7a.8" xml:lang="en">The white sun reddens towards his setting;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-7a.9" xml:lang="en">The bright moon pines and wastes away.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-7a.10" xml:lang="en">All too soon the year will be ended,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-7a.11" xml:lang="en">10 And old age comes creeping on apace.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-7a.12" xml:lang="en">My heart is distraught; its passion increases:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-7a.13" xml:lang="en">I am disappointed; I have nothing to hope for.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-7a.14" xml:lang="en">My breast is bitter with grief and anguish,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-7a.15" xml:lang="en">And sigh after long sigh I heave heavily.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-7a.16" xml:lang="en">15 Swiftly the years roll by, ever receeding,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-7a.17" xml:lang="en">And old age finds me alone, without a place.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-7a.18" xml:lang="en">My affairs press upon me and urge me forward;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-7a.19" xml:lang="en">But I linger on here in uncertainty.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-8a.2" xml:lang="en">1 How the floating clouds drift over everything!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-8a.3" xml:lang="en">See how they suddenly cover the bright moon!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-8a.4" xml:lang="en">My loyalty was shining bright; I longed to make it seen;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-8a.5" xml:lang="en">But the black clouds obscured it and it could not shine through.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-8a.6" xml:lang="en">5 I wanted the shining sun to come out in splendour,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-8a.7" xml:lang="en">But the clouds, dark and thick, came and hid its light.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-8a.8" xml:lang="en">I took no thought for myself, I wished only to be loyal;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-8a.9" xml:lang="en">But others with black, foul blots besmirched my name.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-8a.10" xml:lang="en">The noble actions of Yáo and Shùn</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-8a.11" xml:lang="en">10 Shone with a glory that reached to the skies;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-8a.12" xml:lang="en">Yet the pernicious jealousy of others</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-8a.13" xml:lang="en">Gave them a false report, calling them 'unkind'.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-8a.14" xml:lang="en">Even the sun and moon that shine with so bright a light</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-8a.15" xml:lang="en">Are often dimmed and have flaws upon them.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-8a.16" xml:lang="en">15 Then how much more the affairs of and entire state</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-8a.17" xml:lang="en">That are so many-sided and crookedly involved!</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.2" xml:lang="en">1 A lotus-petal coat is bright and gay to wear,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.3" xml:lang="en">And yet too flimsy to be girded on.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.4" xml:lang="en">He was too proud of his beauty and arrogantly boasted,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.5" xml:lang="en">Rejecting the steadfast loyalty of his ministers.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.6" xml:lang="en">5 He hated the beauty of the truly noble,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.7" xml:lang="en">But he loved a base fellow's blustering bravado.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.8" xml:lang="en">The crowd, all hustling forward, each day advanced in favour;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.9" xml:lang="en">But beauty left, and moved away to far distant places.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.10" xml:lang="en">When the farmer rests his plough and moves about in idleness,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.11" xml:lang="en">10 I fear that field and meadow will be overgrown with weeds.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.12" xml:lang="en">When affairs of state are multiplied all for private ends,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.13" xml:lang="en">I fear that disaster is bound to follow.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.14" xml:lang="en">The world all agree as one and their eyes are dazzled:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.15" xml:lang="en">How blind the way in which they apportion praise and blame!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.16" xml:lang="en">15 Today you deck yourselves and preen before the mirror:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.17" xml:lang="en">Tomorrow you may have to creep away and hide.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.18" xml:lang="en">I wanted to send my message by a shooting star,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.19" xml:lang="en">But he sped too fast and I could not catch up with him.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.20" xml:lang="en">Now the sky above is all veiled by these floating clouds,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.21" xml:lang="en">20 And below is sombre gloom without any light.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.22" xml:lang="en">Because Yáo ond Shùn had those they could trust with office,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.23" xml:lang="en">They were able to sleep sound and lead a life of ease.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.24" xml:lang="en">If, in the whole world, you had earned no man's spite,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.25" xml:lang="en">How could your heart have come by this fearful dread?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.26" xml:lang="en">25 If you drove really noble steeds, rushing as swift as wind,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.27" xml:lang="en">Why would you need to use the coercing whip?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.28" xml:lang="en">Truly, moats and walls are not sufficient safeguard;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.29" xml:lang="en">Though you make your armour doubly thick, it is of no awail.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.30" xml:lang="en">Hoveringly I wait, but come to no conclusion;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.31" xml:lang="en">30 I am plunged in blackest melancholy, constricted with sadness.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.32" xml:lang="en">My passage between heaven and earth seems almost over;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.33" xml:lang="en">Yet I have accomplished nothing; I am without achievements.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.34" xml:lang="en">Willingly I would sink from sight and never more be seen;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.35" xml:lang="en">Yet still I hanker to make my name known in the world.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.36" xml:lang="en">35 So I wander restlessly, but never meet my goal;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.37" xml:lang="en">Wearing myself out - a fool for righteousness!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.38" xml:lang="en">Far and wide I roam, never coming to a stopping-place;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.39" xml:lang="en">Like a bird I swiftly soar, but never alight.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.40" xml:lang="en">The land has a good horse, but knows not how to drive him:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.41" xml:lang="en">40 Why do they wildly search for one elsewhere?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.42" xml:lang="en">When Níng Qī sang beneath his cart,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.43" xml:lang="en">Duke Huán heard him and understood.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.44" xml:lang="en">But now there is no Bó Lè with his good eye for a horse,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.45" xml:lang="en">Who could be found to judge his worth?</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.46" xml:lang="en">45 Often I weep as I brood on these things:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.47" xml:lang="en">I see them most clearly, to my heart's pain.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.48" xml:lang="en">With singleness of purpose, I tried to show my loyalty,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-9a.49" xml:lang="en">But the jealous came between us and screened me from his sight.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-10a.2" xml:lang="en">1 Just grant me my worthless body and let me go away,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-10a.3" xml:lang="en">To set my wandering spirit soaring amidst the clouds;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-10a.4" xml:lang="en">To ride the circling vapours of the primordial ether,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-10a.5" xml:lang="en">Racing the myriad hosts of spirits.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-10a.6" xml:lang="en">5 Bright rainbows darting swiftly in the traces,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-10a.7" xml:lang="en">I shall pass through the thick throngs of the powers of air:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-10a.8" xml:lang="en">On my left the Scarlet Bird, beating his wings,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-10a.9" xml:lang="en">On my right the Green dragon, with undulating coils.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-10a.10" xml:lang="en">With rumblings the Lord of Thunder shall bring up the rear;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-10a.11" xml:lang="en">10 And the rushing Wind God shall lead the way:</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-10a.12" xml:lang="en">Light coaches in the front, creaking as they go;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-10a.13" xml:lang="en">Waggons behind us, slowly trundling.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-10a.14" xml:lang="en">Cloud banners we shall bear, flapping in the wind;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-10a.15" xml:lang="en">A squadron of horsemen shall make a stately escort.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-10a.16" xml:lang="en">15 My plans are firmly fixed and cannot now be altered:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-10a.17" xml:lang="en">I will press forward, resolved to make them prosper.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-10a.18" xml:lang="en">Blessed with rich favours from the Lord of Heaven,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_008-10a.19" xml:lang="en">I shall return to see my lord free from all harm.</seg>
</p>
<p>
</p>
</div>
<div><head>9 招魂	Summons of the Soul</head>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-1a.9" xml:lang="en">The Lord God said to Wū Yáng:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-1a.10" xml:lang="en">'There is a man on earth below whom I would help:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-1a.11" xml:lang="en">His soul has left him. Make divination for him.'</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-1a.12" xml:lang="en">10 Wū Yáng replied:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-1a.13" xml:lang="en">'The Master of Dreams... The Lord God's bidding is hard to follow.' (The Lord God said:)</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-1a.14" xml:lang="en">'You must divine for him,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-1a.15" xml:lang="en">I fear that if you any longer decline,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.1" xml:lang="en">it will be too late.'</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.2" xml:lang="en">15 Wū Yáng thereupon went down and summoned the soul, saying:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.3" xml:lang="en">'O soul, come back! Why have you left your old abode</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.4" xml:lang="en">and fled to the earth's far corners,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.5" xml:lang="en">Deserting the place of your delight</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.6" xml:lang="en">to meet all those things of evil omen?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.7" xml:lang="en">O soul, come back!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.8" xml:lang="en">In the east you cannot abide.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.9" xml:lang="en">There are giants there a thousand fathoms tall, who seek only for souls to catch,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.10" xml:lang="en">20 And ten suns that come out together, melting metal, dissolving stone.180</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.11" xml:lang="en">The folk that live there can bear it, but you, soul, would be consumed.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.12" xml:lang="en">O soul, come back! In the east you cannot abide.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.13" xml:lang="en">O soul, come back!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.14" xml:lang="en">In the south you cannot stay.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.15" xml:lang="en">There the people have tatooed faces and blackened teeth;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.16" xml:lang="en">25 They sacrifice flesh of men</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.17" xml:lang="en">and pound their bones for meat paste.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.18" xml:lang="en">There the venomous cobra abounds, and the great fox that can run a hundred leagues,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.19" xml:lang="en">And the great nine-headed serpent, who darts swiftly this way and that,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.20" xml:lang="en">And swallows men as a sweet relish.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.21" xml:lang="en">O soul, come back!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.22" xml:lang="en">In the south you may not linger.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.23" xml:lang="en">30 'O soul, come back! For the west holds many perils.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.24" xml:lang="en">The Moving Sands stretch on for a hundred leagues.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.25" xml:lang="en">You will be swept up into the Thunder's Chasm,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.26" xml:lang="en">and dashed in pieces, unable to help yourself;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.27" xml:lang="en">And even should you chance to escape from that, beyond is the empty desert,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.28" xml:lang="en">And red ants as huge as elephants and wasps as big as gourds.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.29" xml:lang="en">35 The five grains do not grow there;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.30" xml:lang="en">dry stalks are the only food;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.31" xml:lang="en">And the earth there scorches men up;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.32" xml:lang="en">there is nowhere to look for water;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.33" xml:lang="en">And you will drift there for ever,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.34" xml:lang="en">with nowhere to go i that vastness.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.35" xml:lang="en">O soul, come back! Lest you bring on yourself perdition.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.36" xml:lang="en">'O soul, come back!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.37" xml:lang="en">In the north you may not stay.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.38" xml:lang="en">40 There the layered ice rises high,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.39" xml:lang="en">and the snowflakes fly for a hundred leagues and more.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.40" xml:lang="en">O soul come back!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.41" xml:lang="en">You cannot long say there.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.42" xml:lang="en">O soul, come back! Climb not to the heaven above,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.43" xml:lang="en">For tigers and leopards guard the nine gates, with jaws ever ready to rend 1í up mortal men,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.44" xml:lang="en">And one man with nine heads that can pull up nine thousand trees,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.45" xml:lang="en">45 And the slant-eyed jackal-wolves pad to and fro;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.46" xml:lang="en">They hang out men for sport and drop them in the abyss,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.47" xml:lang="en">And only at God's command may they ever rest or sleep.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.48" xml:lang="en">O soul, come back! Lest you fall into this danger.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.49" xml:lang="en">'O soul, come back!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.50" xml:lang="en">Go not down to the Land of Darkness,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.51" xml:lang="en">50 Where the Earth God lies, nine-coiled,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.52" xml:lang="en">with dreadful horns on his forehead,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.53" xml:lang="en">And a great humped back and bloody thumbs,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.54" xml:lang="en">pursuing men, swift-footed:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.55" xml:lang="en">Three eyes he has in his tiger's head,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.56" xml:lang="en">and his body is like a bull's.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.58" xml:lang="en">O soul, come back!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.59" xml:lang="en">Lest you bring on yourself disaster.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.60" xml:lang="en">'O soul, come back! and enter the gate of the city.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.61" xml:lang="en">55 Skilled priests are here who call you, walking backwards to lead you in.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.62" xml:lang="en">Qín basket-work, silk-chords of Qí, and silken banners of Zhèng:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.63" xml:lang="en">All things are there proper for you to recall; and with long-drawn, piercing cries they summon the wandering soul.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-2a.64" xml:lang="en">O soul, come back! Return to your old abode.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.2" xml:lang="en">'All the quarters of the world are full of harm and evil.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.3" xml:lang="en">60 Hear while I describe for you your quiet and reposeful home.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.4" xml:lang="en">High halls and deep chambers, with railings and tiered balconies;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.5" xml:lang="en">Stepped terraces, storied pavilions, whose tops look on the high mountains;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.6" xml:lang="en">Lattice doors with scarlet interstices, and carving on the square lintels;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.7" xml:lang="en">Draughtless rooms for winter; galleries cool in summer;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.8" xml:lang="en">65 Streams and gullies wind in and out, purling prettily;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.9" xml:lang="en">A warm breeze bends the melilotus and sets the tall orchids swaying.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.10" xml:lang="en">Beyond the hall, in the appartments, the ceilings and floors are vermillion,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.11" xml:lang="en">The chambers of polished stone, with kingfisher curtains hanging from s jasper hooks;</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.12" xml:lang="en">Bedspreads of kingfisher seeded with pearls, dazzling in brightness:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.13" xml:lang="en">70 Arras of fine silk covers the walls; damask canopies stretch overhead,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.14" xml:lang="en">Braids and ribbons, brocades and satins, fastened with rings of precious stone.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.15" xml:lang="en">Many a rich and curious thing is to be seen in the furnishings of the chamber.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.16" xml:lang="en">Bright candles of orchid-perfumed fat lights up flower-like faces that await you;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.17" xml:lang="en">Twice eight handmaids to serve your bed, each night alternating in duty,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.18" xml:lang="en">75 The lovely daughters of noble families, far exelling common maidens.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.19" xml:lang="en">Women with hair dressed finely in many fashions fill your apartmenets,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.20" xml:lang="en">In looks and bearing sweetly compliant, each gently yielding to the other.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.21" xml:lang="en">But, despite their soft looks, of strong and noble natures, lofty spirits.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.22" xml:lang="en">Beauty and elegance grace the inner chambers:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.23" xml:lang="en">80 Mothlike eyebrows and lustrous eyes that dart out beams of brightness,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.24" xml:lang="en">Delicate coloring, soft round flesh, flashing, seductive glances.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.25" xml:lang="en">In your garden pavilion, by the long bed-curtains, they wait your royal pleasure:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.26" xml:lang="en">Of kingfisher feathers its purple curtains and the blue hangings that furnish its high hall;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.27" xml:lang="en">The walls, red; vermillion the woodwork; jet inlay on the roof-beams;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.28" xml:lang="en">85 Overhead you behold carved rafters, painted with dragons and serpents;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.29" xml:lang="en">Seated in the hall, leaning on its balustrade, you look down on a winding pool;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.30" xml:lang="en">Its lotuses have just opened; among them grow water-chesnuts;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.31" xml:lang="en">And purple-stemmed water-mallows enamel the green wave's surface.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.32" xml:lang="en">Attendants quaintly costumed in spotted leopard skins wait on the sloping bank;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.33" xml:lang="en">A light coach is tilted for you to ascend; footmen and riders wait in position.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-3a.34" xml:lang="en">An orchid carpet covers the ground; the hedge is of flowering hibiscus.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.1" xml:lang="en">O soul, come back! Why should you go far away?</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.2" xml:lang="en">'All your household have come to do you honour; all kinds of good food are ready:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.3" xml:lang="en">Rice, broom-corn, early wheat, mixed with yellow millet;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.4" xml:lang="en">95 Bitter, salt, sour, hot and sweet - there are dishes of all flavours:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.5" xml:lang="en">Ribs of the fattened ox, tender and succulent;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.6" xml:lang="en">Sour and bitter blended in the soup of Wú;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.7" xml:lang="en">Stewed turtle and roast kid, served up with yam sauce;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.8" xml:lang="en">Geese cooked in sour sauce, caseroled duck, fried flesh of the great crane;</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.9" xml:lang="en">100 Braised chicken, seetheed terrapin, high-seasoned, but not to spoil the 190 taste;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.10" xml:lang="en">Fried honey-cakes of rice flour and malt-sugar sweetmeats;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.11" xml:lang="en">Jade-like wine, honey-flavoured, fills the winged cups;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.12" xml:lang="en">Ice-cooled liqour, strained of impurities, clear wine, cool and refreshing;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.13" xml:lang="en">Here are laid out patterned ladles, and here is sparkling wine.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.14" xml:lang="en">O soul, come back! Here you shall have respect and nothing shall harm 191 you.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.15" xml:lang="en">192 'Before the dainties have left the tables girl musicians take up their places.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.16" xml:lang="en">They set up the bells and fasten the drums and sing the latest songs:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.17" xml:lang="en">"Crossing the River", "Gathering Caltrops"</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.18" xml:lang="en">and "The Sunny Bank".</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.19" xml:lang="en">The lovely girls are drunk with wine, their faces are flushed.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.20" xml:lang="en">110 With amorous glances and flirting looks, their eyes like wavelets sparkle;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.21" xml:lang="en">Dressed in embroideries, clad in finest silks, splendid but not showy;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.22" xml:lang="en">Their long hair, falling from high chignons, hangs low in lovely tresses.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.23" xml:lang="en">Two rows of eight, in perfect time,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.24" xml:lang="en">perform a dance of Zhèng;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.25" xml:lang="en">Their sleeves rise like crossed bamboo stems,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.26" xml:lang="en">then slowly shimmer downwards.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.27" xml:lang="en">Pipes and zithers rise in wild harmonies,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.28" xml:lang="en">the sounding drums thunderously roll;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.29" xml:lang="en">And the courts of the palace quake and tremble</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.30" xml:lang="en">as they throw themselves into the Whirling Chǔ.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.31" xml:lang="en">Then they sing songs of Wú and ballads of Cài</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.32" xml:lang="en">the catalpa-wood zither's strings 193 are swept.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.33" xml:lang="en">120 Men and women now sit together, mingling freely without distinction;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.34" xml:lang="en">Hat-strings and fastenings come untied: the revel turns to wild disorder.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.35" xml:lang="en">The singing-girls of Zhèng and Wèi come to take their places among the guests;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.36" xml:lang="en">But the dancers of the Whirling Chǔ find favour over all the others.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.37" xml:lang="en">Then with bamboo dice and ivory pieces the game of Liù Bó is begun;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.38" xml:lang="en">125 Sides are taken; they advance together; keenly they threaten each other.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.39" xml:lang="en">Pieces are kinged and the scoring doubled. Shouts of 'five white!' arise.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.40" xml:lang="en">-</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.41" xml:lang="en">-</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.42" xml:lang="en">Day and night are swallowed up in continuous merriment of wine.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.43" xml:lang="en">Bright candles of orchid-perfumed fat burn in stands of delcate tracery.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.44" xml:lang="en">The guests compose snatches to express their thoughts as the orchid fragrance steals over them;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.45" xml:lang="en">130 And those with some object of their affections lovingly tell their verses to each other.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.46" xml:lang="en">In wine they attain the heights of pleasure and give delight to the near departed.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-4a.47" xml:lang="en">O soul, come back! Return to your old abode.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-5a.2" xml:lang="en">LUAN</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-5a.3" xml:lang="en">In the new year, as spring began, we set off for the south.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-5a.4" xml:lang="en">The green duckweed lay on the water, and the white flag flowered.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-5a.5" xml:lang="en">135 Our road passed through Lú-jiāng with Cháng-bó on the right hand.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-5a.6" xml:lang="en">I stood on the marsh's margin and looked far out on the distance.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-5a.7" xml:lang="en">My team was of four jet horses; we set out together a thousand chariots strong.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-5a.8" xml:lang="en">The beaters' fires flickered skyward, and the smoke rose like a pall.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-5a.9" xml:lang="en">I trotted to where the throng was, and galloped ahead to draw them,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-5a.10" xml:lang="en">140 Then reined as we sighted our quarry, and wheeled around to the right hand.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-5a.11" xml:lang="en">I raced with the King in the marshland, to see which of us should take it.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-5a.12" xml:lang="en">The King himself shot the arrow; the rhinoceros turned and fled.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-5a.13" xml:lang="en">'The darkness yields to daylight; we cannot stay much longer.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-5a.14" xml:lang="en">Marsh orchids cover the path here; this way must be too marshy.'</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-5a.15" xml:lang="en">145 On, on the river's waters roll; above them grow woods of maple.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-5a.16" xml:lang="en">The eye travels on a thousand lǐ, and the heart breaks for sorrow.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_009-5a.17" xml:lang="en">O soul, come back! Alas for the Southern Land!</seg>
</p>
<p>
</p>
</div>
<div><head>10 大招</head>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.3" xml:lang="en">1 Green spring follows the old year and the bright sun shines,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.4" xml:lang="en">And the breath of spring stirs, quickening all creation.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.5" xml:lang="en">Dark winter frosts melt away. O soul, do not flee!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.6" xml:lang="en">Oh soul, come back! Do not go far away!</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.7" xml:lang="en">5 O, soul, go not to the east!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.8" xml:lang="en">In the east is the great sea,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.9" xml:lang="en">where the swelling waters billow endlessly,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.10" xml:lang="en">And water-dragons swim side by side,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.11" xml:lang="en">swiftly darting above and below.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.12" xml:lang="en">It is clammy with rain and fog,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.13" xml:lang="en">that glister white and heavy.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.16" xml:lang="en">O, soul, go not to the east,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.17" xml:lang="en">to the desolate Gulf of Brightness!</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.18" xml:lang="en">10 O soul, go not to the south!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.19" xml:lang="en">In the south are a hundred leagues of flaming fire</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.20" xml:lang="en">and coiling cobras;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.21" xml:lang="en">The mountains rise sheer and steep;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.22" xml:lang="en">tigers and leopards slink;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.23" xml:lang="en">The cow-fish is there, and the spit-sand,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.24" xml:lang="en">and the rearing python.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.25" xml:lang="en">O soul, go not to the south!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.26" xml:lang="en">There are monsters there that will harm you.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.27" xml:lang="en">15 O soul, go not to the west!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.28" xml:lang="en">In the west are the Moving Sands</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.29" xml:lang="en">stretching endlessly on and on,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.30" xml:lang="en">And beasts with heads like swine,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.31" xml:lang="en">slanting eyes and shaggy hair,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.32" xml:lang="en">Long claws and serrated teeth,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.33" xml:lang="en">and wild, mad laughter.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.34" xml:lang="en">O soul, go not to the west!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.35" xml:lang="en">In the west are many dangers.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.36" xml:lang="en">20 O soul, go not to the north!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.37" xml:lang="en">In the north are the Frozen Mountain, and the Torch Dragon, glaring red;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.38" xml:lang="en">And the Dài river that cannot be crossed,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.39" xml:lang="en">whose depths are unfathomable;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.40" xml:lang="en">And the sky is white and glittering, and all is congealed with cold.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.41" xml:lang="en">O soul, go not to the north! There is no bourne there to your journeying.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-1a.42" xml:lang="en">25 O soul come back to leisure and quietness!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-2a.2" xml:lang="en">Enjoy yourself in your land of Chǔ, tranquil and untroubled.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-2a.3" xml:lang="en">Indulge your fancies, fulfil your wishes, let your mind be at ease.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-2a.4" xml:lang="en">Number your days out in lasting pleasure, to old age, full of years.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-2a.5" xml:lang="en">O soul, come back to pleasure that cannot be told! 206</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-2a.6" xml:lang="en">30 The five kinds of grain are heaped six ells high, and the corn of zizania.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-2a.7" xml:lang="en">Cauldrons seethe to their brims, wafting a fragrance of weel-blended flavours:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-2a.8" xml:lang="en">Plump orioles, pigeons and geese, flavoured with broth of jackal's meat.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-2a.9" xml:lang="en">O soul, come back! Indulge your appetite!</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-2a.10" xml:lang="en">Fresh turtle, succulent chicken, dressed with the sauce of Chǔ;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-2a.11" xml:lang="en">35 Pickled pork, dog cooked in bitter herbs, and ginger-flavoured mince,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-2a.12" xml:lang="en">And sour Wú salad of artemisia, not too wet or tasteless.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-2a.13" xml:lang="en">O soul, come back! Indulge in your own choice!</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-2a.14" xml:lang="en">Roast crane next is served, steamed duck and broiled quails,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-2a.15" xml:lang="en">Fried bream, stewed magpies, and green goose, broiled.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-2a.16" xml:lang="en">40 O soul, come back! Choice things are spread before you.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-2a.17" xml:lang="en">Four kinds of wine have been subtly blended, not rasping to the throat:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-2a.18" xml:lang="en">Clear, fragrant, ice-cool liqour, not for base men to drink;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-2a.19" xml:lang="en">And white yeast has been mixed with must of Wú to make the clear Chǔ wine.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-2a.20" xml:lang="en">O soul, come back, and do not be afraid.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-3a.2" xml:lang="en">45 Musicians from Dài, Qín, Zhèng and Wèi</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-3a.3" xml:lang="en">are ready with their pipes;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-3a.4" xml:lang="en">They play the 'Jià Biàn' of Fú Xì</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-3a.5" xml:lang="en">and the 'Láo Shāng' of Chǔ.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-3a.6" xml:lang="en">The singers chorus 'The Sunny Bank' to the music of Zhào flutes.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-3a.7" xml:lang="en">O soul, come back and tune the mulberry zither!</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-3a.8" xml:lang="en">Two teams of eight join in a dance to the chanting of poetry;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-3a.9" xml:lang="en">50 Bells and stone-chimes sound in unison as the musicians move into the luàn,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-3a.10" xml:lang="en">And the four trebles blow with all their might as they enter the final modulation.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-3a.11" xml:lang="en">O soul, come back! Listen to their songs and lays!</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-3a.12" xml:lang="en">Ah, the vermeil lips and dazzling teeth, lovely and alluring!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-3a.13" xml:lang="en">The uniformity of exellence, skilfull and imposing!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-3a.14" xml:lang="en">55 The well-rounded flesh and fine bones, elegant and pleasing!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-3a.15" xml:lang="en">O soul, come back to solacing and comfort!</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-3a.16" xml:lang="en">And there are lovely eyes, flashing smiles</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-3a.17" xml:lang="en">from under long, mothlike eybrows,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-3a.18" xml:lang="en">And faces of delicate refinement, glowing with the rosy flush of youth:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-3a.19" xml:lang="en">Beauty overflowing in abundance, goodness and grace to match it.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-3a.20" xml:lang="en">60 O soul, come back! Enjoy this in quietness!</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-3a.24" xml:lang="en">There are plump cheeks and small tilted ears and eyebrows arched compass-fine;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-3a.25" xml:lang="en">The softness and grace of gesture that betokens a generous nature;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-3a.26" xml:lang="en">Small waists and necks long and slender as golden xiān-bēi buckles.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-3a.27" xml:lang="en">O soul, come back! Let resentful thoughts be banished!</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-3a.28" xml:lang="en">65 There are those who bring ease for the heart in every one of their movements;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-3a.29" xml:lang="en">Whose powder and eyebrow black give off a rich perfume.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-3a.30" xml:lang="en">Half-hiding their faces behind long sleeves, well they know how to detain a guest!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-3a.31" xml:lang="en">O soul, come back and fill your night with pleasure!</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-3a.32" xml:lang="en">Ah, the straight brows, jet in hue, the lovely eyes, large and lustruous!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-3a.33" xml:lang="en">70 The dimpling cheeks and fine teeth, flashing in winning smiles!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-3a.34" xml:lang="en">The well-rounded flesh and fine bones, the lithe and graceful limbs!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-3a.35" xml:lang="en">O soul, come back! Enjoy what gives you comfort!</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-4a.2" xml:lang="en">The main hall is large and spacious; the audience chamber resplendent with scarlet woodwork;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-4a.3" xml:lang="en">A solar in the southern building rises high above the roof-eaves;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-4a.4" xml:lang="en">And loggias run round about, and covered walks for exercising beasts in...</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-4a.5" xml:lang="en">Here you may gallop or amble at leisure, or hunt in the spring-quickened park.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-4a.6" xml:lang="en">Jade are the hubs of your chariot, and its chased yoke-bar splendid with patterned adornment.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-4a.7" xml:lang="en">Wild parsnip, orchid and cassia grow thickly beside the way.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-4a.8" xml:lang="en">O soul, come back! Indulge your heart's desire!</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-4a.9" xml:lang="en">80 The gardens are stocked with peacocks; phoenixes too are found there;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-4a.10" xml:lang="en">The jungle-fowl chorus at dawn; bald crane are mixed among them; 214</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-4a.11" xml:lang="en">Swans fly to and fro; green geese wander around.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-4a.12" xml:lang="en">O soul, come back! The phoenixes are hovering.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-4a.13" xml:lang="en">Come the sleek, happy face, and lusty, sanguine health:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-4a.14" xml:lang="en">85 A body that will maintain fitness to ripe old age.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-4a.15" xml:lang="en">Your family and household fill the court, distinguished, all, in rank and office.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-4a.16" xml:lang="en">O soul, come back and dwell at peace in your household!</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-4a.17" xml:lang="en">From all your land, by every road, like the clouds assembling:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-4a.18" xml:lang="en">The great lords of the three sceptres, godlike in giving dooms,</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-4a.19" xml:lang="en">90 Watching over the young and meek, upholding the orphan and the widow.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-4a.20" xml:lang="en">O soul, come back! Let good governance shine forth!</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-5a.2" xml:lang="en">In your lands and domains of a thousand fields your people teem and prosper;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-5a.3" xml:lang="en">Your benignity falls on all classes of men; glorious are your rich favours;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-5a.4" xml:lang="en">Dread goes before you; peaceful arts follow you; the beauty of your goodness is manifest.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-5a.5" xml:lang="en">95 O soul, come back! And rewards and punishments shall be justly meted.</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-5a.6" xml:lang="en">Your fair fame, like the sun, shines over every land;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-5a.7" xml:lang="en">The report of your goodness equals Heaven's; myriads live in your peace.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-5a.8" xml:lang="en">North up to Yōu-líng and south as far as Jiāo-zhǐ;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-5a.9" xml:lang="en">West all the way to the Sheep's Gut Pass and eastward to the sea's edge.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-5a.10" xml:lang="en">100 O soul, come back! Raise up good men to office!</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-5a.11" xml:lang="en">Proclaim your rule! Show forth your acts! Restrain the cruel oppressor!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-5a.12" xml:lang="en">Lift up exellence to the place of councel! Punish the infamous and mean!</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-5a.13" xml:lang="en">The Just and Good sits on the throne, most like Great Yǔ in his command.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-5a.14" xml:lang="en">The flower of chivalry hold governance, from whom flows favour over all.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-5a.15" xml:lang="en">105 O soul, come back, and let the state be ruled!</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-5a.16" xml:lang="en">In glory and majesty your godlike power is revealed.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-5a.17" xml:lang="en">With stately mien your Dukes ascend and descend in the hall.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-5a.18" xml:lang="en">The princes are all assembled; the Nine Ministers have taken their places;</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-5a.19" xml:lang="en">The butts are clearly marked out; the leather targets are stretched:</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-5a.20" xml:lang="en">110 Holding their bows and grasping their arrows, they bow and defer with ceremonial courtesies.</seg>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-5a.22" xml:lang="en">Sorrow for Troth Betrayed</seg>
</p>
<p>
<seg corresp="#KR4a0001_tls_010-5a.23" xml:lang="en">O soul, come back! Revive the ways of the Three Kings of old!</seg>
</p>
<p>
</p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
